<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:stmml="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml_1.1" packageId="edi.18.1" system="https://pasta.lternet.edu" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1  http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.1/eml.xsd">
  <access scope="document" order="allowFirst" authSystem="edi">
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=csmith,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset>
    <title>Massachusetts Department of Conservation and Recreation (DCR): Quabbin Reservoir and Ware River watershed sampling program, 1987-2013</title>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Paúl</givenName>
        <surName>Reyes</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Massachusetts Department of Conservation and Recreation Office of Watershed Management</organizationName>
      <positionName>Environmental Engineer</positionName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>485 Ware Road</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Belchertown</city>
        <administrativeArea>MA</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>01007</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">413-323-6921, ext. 307</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>paul.reyes@state.ma.us</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <pubDate>2017-04-05</pubDate>
    <abstract>
      <para>This report is a summary of water quality monitoring results from twenty-four surface water stations established throughout the Quabbin Reservoir and Ware River watersheds and other special investigative samples. The Department of Conservation and Recreation, Division of Water Supply Protection is the state agency charged with the responsibility of managing Quabbin Reservoir and its surrounding natural resources in order to protect, preserve and enhance the environment of the Commonwealth and to assure the availability of pure water to future generations. As part of this effort, the Environmental Quality Section maintains a comprehensive water quality monitoring program to ensure that Quabbin Reservoir and its tributaries meet state water quality standards. As part of this task, the Environmental Quality Section performs the necessary field work, interprets water quality data and prepares reports of findings. This annual summary is intended to meet the needs of the decision lakers, the concerned public and others whose decisions must reflect water quality considerations. Reservoir water quality data collected by the DCR documents consistently reliable source water quality that fully meets the stringent source water quality criteria stipulated under the Surface Water Treatment Rule. Water quality data are collected monthly except during periods of adverse weather and ice conditions in the winter. Three sampling stations that were routinely sampled in 2010 are profiled in Table 5. Figure 4 may be referenced for the specific locations of each sample site.</para>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>Massachusetts</keyword>
      <keyword>Long-term monitoring</keyword>
      <keyword>Quabbin</keyword>
      <keyword>drinking water</keyword>
      <keyword>reservoir</keyword>
    </keywordSet>
    <intellectualRights>
      <para>
  This information is released to the public under the Creative Commons
  license CC0 1.0 Universal
  (https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/) and may be used
  for academic, educational, or commercial purposes subject to the
  following restrictions: The Data User must realize that these data
  sets are being actively used by others for ongoing research and that
  coordination may be necessary to prevent duplicate publication. The
  Data User is urged to contact the data creators or contacts. Where
  appropriate, the Data User may be encouraged to consider collaboration
  and/or co-authorship with original investigators. The Data User must
  realize that the data may be misinterpreted if taken out of context.
  The Data User must acknowledge use of the data by an appropriate
  citation (suggested format includes the DOI). While substantial
  efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation,
  complete accuracy of data sets cannot be guaranteed. All data are made
  available "as is". The creators shall not be liable for
  damages resulting from any use or misinterpretation of data sets. Data
  users should be aware that we periodically update data sets. By using
  these data, the Data User agrees to abide by the terms of this
  agreement. Thank you for your cooperation.
</para>
    </intellectualRights>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Quabbin Reservoir and Ware River watersheds, MA, USA</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-72.26</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-72.0</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>42.33</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>42.13</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1987-01-01</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2013-05-31</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <contact>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Paúl</givenName>
        <surName>Reyes</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Massachusetts Department of Conservation and Recreation Office of Watershed Management</organizationName>
      <positionName>Environmental Engineer</positionName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>485 Ware Road</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Belchertown</city>
        <administrativeArea>MA</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>01007</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">413-323-6921, ext. 307</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>paul.reyes@state.ma.us</electronicMailAddress>
    </contact>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <title>Lab analyses</title>
            <para>Water samples are collected at depth using a Kemmerer bottle, and samples are analyzed at Quabbin Laboratory for turbidity, alkalinity, and bacteria.</para>
            <para>When a specific depth isn’t noted in the “Site” column, samples were likely taken “just below the surface of the reservoir.”</para>
            <para>If a depth is noted in the “Site” column, samples were “taken at the surface (0.5 meter), mid-depth, and within 2 to 3 meters of bottom when the reservoir is not thermally stratified…When the reservoir is stratified… from the surface (0.5 meters), mid-metalimnion (generally 9 to 14 meters), and deep (within 2 to 3 meters of bottom).” The depth is indicated in “Site” column with the letters (D, S, and M).</para>
            <para>Turbidity (TURB): Weekly samples from 1987 to 2005, monthly samples from 2005 to 2013 - SM_2130B</para>
            <para>pH: Weekly samples from 1987 to 2005. Additionally monthly samples in 2007 - Eureka Manta Multiparameter Probe, EPA Method 150.1 using Orion 920A+ pH Meter</para>
            <para>Alkalinity (EPAALK &amp; STDALK): Weekly samples from 1987 to 2005, monthly samples from 2005 to 2013 - SM 2320B</para>
            <para>Dissolved Oxygen (DOPPM &amp; DOSAT): Weekly samples form 1987 to 2005 - Eureka Manta Multiparameter Probe</para>
            <para>Temperature °C (TEMPC): Weekly samples from 1987 to 2005 - Eureka Manta Multiparameter Probe</para>
            <para>Specific Conductance (SPCOND): Weekly, bi-weekly, and monthly samples depending on the year - Eureka Manta Multiparameter Probe</para>
            <para>Nitrate (NO3-): “Nutrients are monitored quarterly at the WDF and in-reservoir at Site 202… Nutrient analyses were typically conducted on samples collected in May, July, October, and December to coincide with different stages of reservoir stratification.</para>
            <para>Total Kjeldahl nitrogen (TKN): “Nutrients are monitored quarterly at the WDF and in-reservoir at Site 202… Nutrient analyses were typically conducted on samples collected in May, July, October, and December to coincide with different stages of reservoir stratification.”</para>
            <para>Total Phosphorus (TPH): “Nutrients are monitored quarterly at the WDF and in-reservoir at Site 202… Nutrient analyses were typically conducted on samples collected in May, July, October, and December to coincide with different stages of reservoir stratification.”</para>
            <para>Silica (SiO2): Quarterly sampling…was performed at the onset of thermal stratification (May), in the middle of the stratification period (late July), near the end of the stratification period (October), and during a winter period of isothermy (December)</para>
            <para>Ammonia (NH3): “Quarterly sampling…was performed at the onset of thermal stratification (May), in the middle of the stratification period (late July), near the end of the stratification period (October), and during a winter period of isothermy (December).”</para>
            <para>Calcium (Ca++): “Calcium monitoring was started in 2010 at the three in-reservoir sampling stations (Site 202, Site 206, and Den Hill) to evaluate risk of aquatic invasive organisms colonization (e.g., zebra mussels). Begun on a monthly basis at three depths, calcium monitoring was reduced to a quarterly frequency at one depth because of the low concentrations and low variability at these in-reservoir sampling stations.”</para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <sampling>
        <studyExtent>
          <description>
            <para>Twenty-four surface water stations established throughout the Quabbin Reservoir and Ware River watersheds</para>
          </description>
        </studyExtent>
        <samplingDescription>
          <para>Reservoir water inside the three distinct reservoir basins is sampled monthly from April through December, weather permitting. Water samples are collected at depth using a Kemmerer bottle, and samples are analyzed at Quabbin Laboratory for turbidity, alkalinity, and bacteria. Samples for total and fecal coliform bacteria are taken at the surface (0.5 meter), 6 meters, and either the respective water supply intake depth (18 meters for Site 202, 24 meters for Site 206) or a deep sample (13 meters at Den Hill). Physicochemical grab samples are taken at the surface (0.5 meter), mid-depth, and within 2 to 3 meters of bottom when the reservoir is not thermally stratified. When the reservoir is stratified, physicochemical samples are collected from the surface (0.5 meters), mid-metalimnion (generally 9 to 14 meters), and deep (within 2 to 3 meters of bottom).
Quarterly sampling for nutrients was performed at the onset of thermal stratification (May), in
the middle of the stratification period (late July), near the end of the stratification period
(October), and during a winter period of isothermy (December). The MWRA Central Laboratory provided analytical support for the measurement of total phosphorus, total Kjeldahl nitrogen, nitrate, ammonia, UV254, and silica, calcium monitoring will continue on a monthly schedule as in 2010. Sampling at the three deep-water reservoir stations will continue, with temperature, dissolved oxygen, pH and conductivity profiles collected monthly. The reservoir nutrient sampling program…has been conducted quarterly.</para>
        </samplingDescription>
      </sampling>
    </methods>
    <dataTable>
      <entityName>MA_QUABBIN_CHEM.csv</entityName>
      <entityDescription>Massachusetts Department of Conservation and Recreation (DCR): Quabbin Reservoir and Ware River watershed sampling program, 1987-2013</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>MA_QUABBIN_CHEM.csv</objectName>
        <size unit="bytes">55078</size>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url>https://lter.limnology.wisc.edu/sites/default/files/data/LAGOS_NE_LIMNO_RAWDATA/MA_QUABBIN_CHEM/MA_QUABBIN_CHEM.csv</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>SITE</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Sample site Depth is sometimes noted in the Site column with D = deep, S = surface, and M = mid-depth. When depth is not noted samples likely are surface.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Sample site Depth is sometimes noted in the Site column with D = deep, S = surface, and M = mid-depth. When depth is not noted samples likely are surface.</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>DATE</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Sample date</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>date</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>mm/dd/yyyy</formatString>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>TURB</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Turbidity (NTU)</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>pH</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>pH</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>STDALK</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Alkalinity</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>milligramsPerLiter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>EPAALK</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Alkalinity</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>milligramsPerLiter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>DOPPM</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Oxygen, dissolved</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>milligramsPerLiter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>TEMPC</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Temperature</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>celsius</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>SPCOND</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Conductance, specific</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>microsiemensPerCentimeter</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>natural</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>TNTC</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Too Numerous To Count</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Too Numerous To Count</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>NO3</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Nitrogen, nitrate (NO3)</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>milligramsPerLiter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>TKN</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Nitrogen, total kjeldahl</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>milligramsPerLiter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>TPH</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Phosphorus, total</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>milligramsPerLiter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>SiO2</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Silica</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>milligramsPerLiter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>natural</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>NH3</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Nitrogen, NH3</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>milligramsPerLiter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Ca</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Calcium</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>milligramsPerLiter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>natural</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
    </dataTable>
    <otherEntity>
      <entityName>DataImport_MA_QUABBIN_CHEM.R</entityName>
      <entityDescription>Imports data for the LAke multi-scaled GeOSpatial database (LAGOS)</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>DataImport_MA_QUABBIN_CHEM.R</objectName>
        <size unit="bytes">19252</size>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>0</numHeaderLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter></fieldDelimiter>
              <quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url>https://lter.limnology.wisc.edu/sites/default/files/data/LAGOS_NE_LIMNO_RAWDATA/MA_QUABBIN_CHEM/DataImport_MA_QUABBIN_CHEM.R</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <entityType>R code</entityType>
    </otherEntity>
  </dataset>
  <additionalMetadata>
    <metadata>
      <stmml:unitList xmlns:stmml="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml_1.1">
        <unit id="microsiemensPerCentimeter" name="microsiemensPerCentimeter" parentSI="siemenPerMeter" unitType="conductance" multiplierToSI="0.1">
          <description>micro siemens Per Centimeter</description>
        </unit>
      </stmml:unitList>
    </metadata>
  </additionalMetadata>
</eml:eml>