<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<eml:eml xmlns:eml="https://eml.ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xmlns:stmml="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.2" packageId="edi.580.2"
  xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0  https://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.2.0/xsd/eml.xsd"
  system="edi">
  <access authSystem="https://pasta.edirepository.org/authentication" order="allowFirst"
    scope="document">
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=edi,o=EDI,dc=edirepository,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset>
    <title>Projected Snow Cover Reductions and Mid-latitude Cyclone Responses in the North American
      Great Plains, 1986 - 2005</title>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Ryan</givenName>
        <givenName>M</givenName>
        <surName>Clare</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>NRL-MRY</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>ryan.clare.ctr@nrlmry.navy.mil</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Ankur</givenName>
        <givenName>R</givenName>
        <surName>Desai</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>UW-Madison</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>desai@aos.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5226-6041</userId>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Michael</givenName>
        <surName>Notaro</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Nelson Center for Climate Research, UW-Madison</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>mnotaro@wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Jonathan</givenName>
        <givenName>E</givenName>
        <surName>Martin</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>UW-Madison</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>jemarti1@wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Stephen</givenName>
        <givenName>J</givenName>
        <surName>Vavrus</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Nelson Center for Climate Research, UW-Madison</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>sjvavrus@wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7612-3109</userId>
    </creator>
    <pubDate>2020-07-27</pubDate>
    <abstract>
      <para>Extratropical cyclones are responsible for major weather events and trends in the
        mid-latitudes and preferentially develop in regions of enhanced cyclogenesis and proceed
        along climatological storm tracks. It has been shown that terrestrial snow cover exerts
        considerable influence on atmospheric baroclinicity which is largely responsible for the
        aforementioned cyclogeneses and storm tracks. Research about the effect which terrestrial
        snow cover exerts on cyclones' intensities, trajectories, and precipitation characteristics
        is limited but indicates a robust relationship with these factors. Many examinations of
        climate model projections have generally shown a poleward shift in storm tracks by the late
        21st century though none have determined the degree to which the coincident poleward shift
        in snow extent is responsible. </para>
      <para>A method of imposing 10th, 50th, and 90th percentile values of snow retreat between the
        late 20th and 21st centuries as projected by 14 models of the Coupled Model Intercomparison
        Project Phase Five (CMIP5) is used to alter 20 historical cold season cyclones which tracked
        over or adjacent to the North American Great Plains. Simulations by the Advanced Research
        version of the Weather Research and Forecast Model (WRF-ARW) are initialized at 0 to 4 days
        prior to cyclogenesis. Including control and sensitivity testing wherein snow is unaltered
        or removed entirely, each cyclone case is simulated 25 times for a total of 500
        simulations.&#13; </para>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>WRF</keyword>
      <keyword>WRF-ARW</keyword>
      <keyword>Snow cover</keyword>
      <keyword>Extratropical cyclone</keyword>
      <keyword>Midlatitude cyclone</keyword>
      <keyword>Baroclinicity</keyword>
      <keyword>Surface forcing</keyword>
      <keyword>Integrated kinetic energy</keyword>
      <keyword>Winter storm</keyword>
      <keyword>Climate change</keyword>
    </keywordSet>
    <intellectualRights>
      <para>This information is released under the Creative Commons license - Attribution - CC BY
        (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). The consumer of these data (\"Data User\"
        herein) is required to cite it appropriately in any publication that results from its use.
        The Data User should realize that these data may be actively used by others for ongoing
        research and that coordination may be necessary to prevent duplicate publication. The Data
        User is urged to contact the authors of these data if any questions about methodology or
        results occur. Where appropriate, the Data User is encouraged to consider collaboration or
        co-authorship with the authors. The Data User should realize that misinterpretation of data
        may occur if used out of context of the original study. While substantial efforts are made
        to ensure the accuracy of data and associated documentation, complete accuracy of data sets
        cannot be guaranteed. All data are made available \"as is.\" The Data User should be aware,
        however, that data are updated periodically and it is the responsibility of the Data User to
        check for new versions of the data. The data authors and the repository where these data
        were obtained shall not be liable for damages resulting from any use or misinterpretation of
        the data. Thank you. </para>
    </intellectualRights>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Continental United States (CONUS) and surrounding regions, lambert conformal projection centered at 43.5 N 98 W with resolution of 30 km.</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-149.991</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-46.001</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>63.041</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>19.306</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1986-01-17</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2005-11-11</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <maintenance>
      <description>completed</description>
    </maintenance>
    <contact>
      <organizationName>EDI</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>info@environmentaldatainitiative.org</electronicMailAddress>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Ryan</givenName>
        <givenName>M</givenName>
        <surName>Clare</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>NRL-MRY</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>ryan.clare.ctr@nrlmry.navy.mil</electronicMailAddress>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Ankur</givenName>
        <givenName>R</givenName>
        <surName>Desai</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>UW-Madison</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>desai@aos.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5226-6041</userId>
    </contact>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>please also see protocol.pdf</para>
          <section>
            <title>Experimental design and data</title>
            <para>In order to test the effect of snow line position on extratropical cyclones, 20
              North American cold season cyclones between 1986-2005 were simulated using the
              Advanced Research core of the NCAR Weather Research and Forecasting model (WRF-ARW)
              version 4.0.3 with perturbed snow cover extent (SCE). Four cyclone cases were
              subjectively selected from each of the months from November through March based on
              manual observational evaluation of all mid-latitude cyclones identified by
              low-pressure centers through this period in daily surface and upper-level weather
              charts. The criteria of selected cases required storm trajectories over or adjacent to
              the Great Plains study area which resemble either the Alberta Clipper track or that of
              the Colorado Low with lifetimes of at least 2 days, based on presence of well-defined
              central minimum pressure. Cases were chosen until a sufficient variety of differences
              in the lifetime minimum sea-level pressure (SLP) and magnitude of upper level forcings
              in the form of 500 hPa height curvature and vorticity advection by the thermal wind
              were found. Cases were simulated with observed initial conditions and validated
              against observations using the 32-km spatial resolution North American Regional
              Reanalysis (NARR) to ensure that WRF could accurately simulate each case.</para>
            <para>Alterations to the SCE of each case were made by applying average poleward snow
              line retreat (PSLR) from the 20-year periods of 1986-2005 (historical) to 2080-2099
              (projected) for each of the five months examined in this study. Projected PSLR was
              determined by examination of the grid cell snow mass change in 14 models of the 5th
              phase of the Coupled Model Intercomparison Project (CMIP5; Taylor et al. 2012; doi in
              Data Provenance table) wherein daily snow mass data were available and experiments
              were conducted with two Representative Concentration Pathway forcings: RCP4.5 and
              RCP8.5. Grid cells were identified as snow-covered if their simulated snow mass was at
              least 5 kg m-2, which corresponds to typically 5 cm of snow depth (assuming a 10:1
              snow to water ratio), sufficient to cover the surface. We did test other thresholds
              and did not find a strong sensitivity to this choice in the projected snow cover maps.
              The southernmost such grid cells were considered to comprise the snow line if the 5
              degree span to the north of a cell had an average snow mass exceeding that threshold.
              This search radius was employed in order to exclude outlying isolated southern patches
              of snow. To limit artifacts that arise from small-scale variability in snow cover, a
              600 km moving window average was then applied to all derived southern extent of snow
              cover, hereafter referred to as the snow line. For each month, the 20-year average
              snow line of the historical and projected periods was calculated, and the amount of
              projected PSLR was determined from west to east in 30 km-wide bins across North
              America. Different iterations, realizations, and physics options belonging to
              experiments of the same model were combined in a one model, one vote scheme. With PSLR
              calculated for both RCP forcings for each of the 14 models, each month contained 28
              PSLR values from which the 10th, 50th, and 90th percentiles were determined. </para>
            <para>The modeling effort involved simulating each of the 20 mid-latitude cyclone cases
              with five degrees of snow line perturbation, each at five different initialization
              times, from zero to four days prior to cyclogenesis, yielding a total of 500 distinct
              simulations. One hundred simulations were generated without changes made to snow cover
              (control). The remaining 400 runs imposed projected snow line changes of varying
              magnitude (10th, 50th, and 90th percentiles) or complete snow removal across the
              domain in order to determine the degree to which the position of the snow line
              influences storms as opposed to that attributable solely to snow removal. Snow lines
              for perturbed simulations were determined by applying values of PSLR to corresponding
              30 km bins of the snow lines, as determined based on the method above, for each case
              and removing all snow south of the new snow line except at altitudes greater than
              2,000 m, where snowpack may persist even in warmer climates. It should be noted that
              the removal of all snow south of the assigned snow line creates a discontinuous step
              function in snow depth, a hard margin which is not necessarily characteristic of real
              snow extent boundaries.</para>
          </section>
          <section>
            <title>WRF model configuration</title>
            <para>All WRF-ARW simulations were executed in the same domain comprised of the
              continental United States (CONUS), central and southern Canada, northern Mexico, and
              the surrounding oceans. 30 km horizontal resolution was used to best capture synoptic
              scale transport with a 150 km buffer zone on each side and 45 vertical levels. Initial
              and lateral boundary conditions were acquired from 3-hour NARR data provided in grib
              format by NOAA/OAR/ESRL PSD, Boulder, Colorado, USA, at
              https://www.esrl.noaa.gov/psd/. Version 4.0 of WRF offers a CONUS suite of physics
              options which was used in this experiment. The NOAH Land Surface Model (Noah LSM) was
              altered to reduce surface snow accumulation to zero during simulation in order to
              avoid snow deposition prior to the arrival of the cyclone of interest into the area
              without removing precipitation in the atmosphere. The Noah LSM uses a single layer
              snow model which calculates the albedo of the snow-covered portion of a grid cell
              as</para>
            <para>∝_snow= ∝_max A^(t^B )</para>
            <para>where αmax is the maximum albedo for fresh snow in the given grid cell, t is the
              age of the snow in days, and A and B are coefficients which are, respectively, 0.94
              and 0.58 (0.82 and 0.46) during periods of accumulation (ablation). Coefficients A and
              B were set to accumulation phase for simulations in every month except for March, when
              the snow was considered to be ablating. </para>
          </section>
          <section>
            <title>Data Information</title>
            <para>Desciptions of variables within each netCDF file are available in the attached
              file, WRF_output_variables.txt. The file may also be found at
              http://co2.aos.wisc.edu/data/snowcover/outputs/WRF_output_variables.txt.
              Alternatively, if users have netCDF installed, data for each file can be viewed in a
              Linux terminal with the command:</para>
            <para>$ ncdump –h filename </para>
            <para>Filename Convention</para>
            <para>case number_T-days initialized prior_perturbation degree_datetime string </para>
            <para>e.g. Case00_T-1_fif_1993-01-30_03:00:00</para>
            <para/>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>This method step describes provenance-based metadata as specified in the LTER EML
            Best Practices.</para>
          <para>This provenance metadata does not contain entity specific information.</para>
        </description>
        <dataSource>
          <title>North American Regional Reanalysis (NARR)</title>
          <creator>
            <individualName>
              <givenName>Fedor</givenName>
              <surName> Mesinger</surName>
            </individualName>
            <electronicMailAddress>fedor.mesinger@sanu.ac.rs</electronicMailAddress>
          </creator>
          <distribution>
            <online>
              <onlineDescription>This online link references a paper that describes data used in the
                creation of this derivative data package.</onlineDescription>
              <url function="information">https://doi.org/10.1175/BAMS-87-3-343</url>
            </online>
          </distribution>
          <contact>
            <individualName>
              <givenName>Perry</givenName>
              <surName>Shafran</surName>
            </individualName>
            <electronicMailAddress>perry.shafran@noaa.org</electronicMailAddress>
          </contact>
        </dataSource>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>This method step describes provenance-based metadata as specified in the LTER EML
            Best Practices.</para>
          <para>This provenance metadata does not contain entity specific information.</para>
        </description>
        <dataSource>
          <title>Community Model Intercomparison Project, Phase 5 (CMIP5)</title>
          <creator>
            <individualName>
              <givenName>Karl</givenName>
              <surName>Taylor</surName>
            </individualName>
            <electronicMailAddress>taylor13@llnl.gov</electronicMailAddress>
          </creator>
          <distribution>
            <online>
              <onlineDescription>This online link references a paper that describes data used in the
                creation of this derivative data package.</onlineDescription>
              <url function="information">https://doi.org/10.1175/BAMS-D-11-00094.1</url>
            </online>
          </distribution>
          <contact>
            <individualName>
              <givenName>Karl</givenName>
              <surName>Taylor</surName>
            </individualName>
            <electronicMailAddress>taylor13@llnl.gov</electronicMailAddress>
          </contact>
        </dataSource>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <project>
      <title>Does Northern Hemisphere Snow Cover Influence Mid­latitude Cyclone Trajectories? Weather System Implications for a Changing Climate</title>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Ankur</givenName>
          <givenName>R</givenName>
          <surName>Desai</surName>
        </individualName>
        <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5226-6041</userId>
        <role>Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <funding>NSF 1640452</funding>
    </project>
    <otherEntity>
      <entityName>off-line data</entityName>
      <entityDescription>the model output is available upon request, please contact EDI info@environmentaldatainitiative.org</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>Snow Cyclone Model output</objectName>
        <dataFormat>
          <externallyDefinedFormat>
            <formatName>netCDF</formatName>
          </externallyDefinedFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <offline>
            <mediumName>external hard drive</mediumName>
          </offline>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <entityType>unknown</entityType>
    </otherEntity>
    <dataTable>
      <entityName>SnowCyclone_manifest.csv</entityName>
      <entityDescription>Manifest file with metadata for off-line netCDF files</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>SnowCyclone_manifest.csv</objectName>
        <size unit="bytes">2788917</size>
        <authentication method="MD5">f4dcc9b761a9c4992dea9056abad4caa</authentication>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
              <quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url>https://lter.limnology.wisc.edu/sites/default/files/data_to_edi/SnowCyclone_manifest.csv</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Case_ID</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Case identifier</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Case identifier</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Initialization_time_days</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Initial time to days</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Initial time to days</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Perturbation_type</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>perturbation type</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>perturbation type</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Month</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>month</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>month</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Filename</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>file name, format case number_T-days initialized prior_perturbation degree_datetime string</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>file name, format case number_T-days initialized prior_perturbation degree_datetime string</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Format</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>file format</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>file format</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Datetime</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>date time</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>date</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>YYYY-MM-DD hh:mm:ss</formatString>
              <dateTimeDomain/>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Interval_hours</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>interval number of hours</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>natural</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">3</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">3</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Checksum</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>checksum of file</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>checksum of file</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
      <numberOfRecords>19575</numberOfRecords>
    </dataTable>
    <otherEntity>
      <entityName>WRF_output_variables.txt</entityName>
      <entityDescription>output variables</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>WRF_output_variables.txt</objectName>
        <size unit="bytes">53591</size>
        <authentication method="MD5">8dbb4b06ccf6e714bf2a0af9358f0384</authentication>
        <dataFormat>
          <externallyDefinedFormat>
            <formatName>text</formatName>
          </externallyDefinedFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url>https://lter.limnology.wisc.edu/sites/default/files/data_to_edi/WRF_output_variables.txt</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <entityType>text</entityType>
    </otherEntity>
    <otherEntity>
      <entityName>protocol.pdf</entityName>
      <entityDescription>formatted methods description</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>protocol.pdf</objectName>
        <size unit="bytes">167340</size>
        <authentication method="MD5">93bc9e0bb5c946ea4af110163613c7c8</authentication>
        <dataFormat>
          <externallyDefinedFormat>
            <formatName>pdf</formatName>
          </externallyDefinedFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url>https://lter.limnology.wisc.edu/sites/default/files/data_to_edi/protocol.pdf</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <entityType>pdf</entityType>
    </otherEntity>
  </dataset>
</eml:eml>
