<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<eml:eml packageId="emifergus.78.1" system="knb" xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 eml.xsd">
 <dataset>
  <title>Douglas Lake (MI) South Fishtail Bay Secchi Depth dataset</title>
  <creator id="1350077836041">
   <individualName>
    <givenName>Bob</givenName>
    <surName>Vande Kopple</surName>
   </individualName>
   <organizationName>University of Michigan Biological Station</organizationName>
   <positionName>Field Station Manager</positionName>
   <address>
    <deliveryPoint>9133 Biological Road</deliveryPoint>
    <city>Pellston</city>
    <administrativeArea>MI</administrativeArea>
    <postalCode>49769</postalCode>
    <country>USA</country>
   </address>
   <phone phonetype="voice">231-539-8407</phone>
   <electronicMailAddress>bvk@umich.edu</electronicMailAddress>
  </creator>
  <abstract>
   <para>Secchi depth readings for South Fishtail Bay, Douglas Lake, MI taken by associates of the
    University of Michigan Biological Station (UMBS). First reading is from 1925 but sampling
    intensity increases in the 1970's. Values range from 2.25 m to 7 m. In the early 1970s the
    University of Michigan Biological Station initiated a series of research projects concerning the
    quality of the lakes in Northern Michigan under the support of the National Science Foundation
    through the Research Applied to National Needs (RANN) program. Dr. John Gannon joined the
    Biological Station's staff in 1972 and directed this program for six years. This research had
    significant impacts on water quality management of lakes throughout Northern Michigan. The
    Biological Station continued to receive grants for water quality research for several years
    after the RANN program had terminated. The Tip of the Mitt Watershed Council has coordinated and
    sponsored the Volunteer Lake Monitoring Program for over 20 years. Presently, volunteers monitor
    35 lakes spread throughout Antrim, Charlevoix, Cheboygan, Emmet, and Montmorency Counties (map
    below). The objectives of the program are to collect baseline data, characterize lake
    ecosystems, identify specific water quality problems, determine water quality trends, and, most
    importantly, inform and educate the public regarding water quality issues and aquatic ecology.
    Monitoring water quality does not ensure clean water, but rather provides valuable information
    to help protect and improve water quality in the lakes of northern Lower Peninsula of
    Michigan.</para>
  </abstract>
  <keywordSet>
   <keyword>Michigan</keyword>
   <keyword>Secchi</keyword>
  </keywordSet>
  <intellectualRights>
   <para>Data belong to the University of Michigan Biological Station The use of Data Sets made
    available by the University of Michigan Biological Station (the Biological Station) is subject
    to the following restrictions and qualifications: 1. The Data User will acknowledge the Data
    Originator and the Biological Station in any publications, reports, or presentations that use
    data falling under the auspices of the Biological Station. Where such products result from the
    use of data secured through the Biological Station, the Data User is strongly urged to consider
    collaboration and/or co-authorship with the Data Originator as appropriate in conformance with
    common academic practices for attribution of authorship and recognition of contribution. Data
    Sets should be cited in the general form: Data Originator, Year Published.Data Set title.
    Publisher: Data Set Identifier. Date Accessed. For example: Miller, D., 2010. Water profiles of
    the Southfishtail Bay Depression in Douglas Lake, Michigan, 1933-1934. Pellston, MI: University
    of Michigan Biological Station Information Management System: UMBS0001. Accessed on 2008-05-14.
    2. The Data User will provide three (3) hard copies or a Portable Document Format (PDF) version
    of all published papers and reports derived from Data Sets obtained via the Biological Station
    to the Data Originator and to the Biological Station Resident Biologist per Section 5., above,
    within 6 months of publication. 3. The Data User agrees not to disseminate or re-distribute data
    supplied by the Biological Station beyond the immediate collaboration. 4. Products generated by
    the Data User from Data Sets supplied by the Biological Station may be used by researchers and
    organizations for research or educational purposes only but not for the generation of income and
    not in any way that would require provision of license rights to such Data Sets. The Data User
    agrees to make these products publicly available in a timely manner as provided in the same
    periods as specified in Section 3., above, for provision of Data Setsto the Biological Station.
    5. The Data User is fully responsible for all errors in analysis and judgment that are derived
    by the Data User from Data Sets made available by the Biological Station. 6. Violation of any of
    the terms of this Data Use Agreement by the Data User will result in the immediate forfeiture of
    allData Sets supplied by the Biological Station and the denial of future use of Data Sets
    archived by the Biological Station.</para>
  </intellectualRights>
  <coverage>
   <geographicCoverage>
    <geographicDescription>Douglas Lake, MI</geographicDescription>
    <boundingCoordinates>
     <westBoundingCoordinate>-84.44</westBoundingCoordinate>
     <eastBoundingCoordinate>-84.37</eastBoundingCoordinate>
     <northBoundingCoordinate>45.36</northBoundingCoordinate>
     <southBoundingCoordinate>45.33</southBoundingCoordinate>
    </boundingCoordinates>
   </geographicCoverage>
   <temporalCoverage>
    <rangeOfDates>
     <beginDate>
      <calendarDate>1925</calendarDate>
     </beginDate>
     <endDate>
      <calendarDate>2011</calendarDate>
     </endDate>
    </rangeOfDates>
   </temporalCoverage>
  </coverage>
  <contact>
   <references>1350077836041</references>
  </contact>
  <methods>
   <methodStep>
    <description>
     <section>
      <title>Secchi Reading</title>
      <para>Starting in May or early June, they start their weekly visits to the deepest part of the
       lake to perform water quality monitoring activities. After anchoring the boat, the monitor
       begins by measuring water clarity with a Secchi disc. The monitor slowly lowers the Secchi
       disc over the shaded side of the boat and notes the depth where it disappears. The disc is
       lowered an additional two feet and then slowly raised until coming back into view. After
       noting the depth of reappearance, the average of the two depths is calculated and
       recorded.</para>
     </section>
    </description>
    <instrumentation>Secchi disk</instrumentation>
   </methodStep>
   <sampling>
    <studyExtent>
     <description>
      <para>Douglas Lake, MI</para>
     </description>
    </studyExtent>
    <samplingDescription>
     <para>Deepest part of the lake. Secchi depths observations occured monthly throughout the year
      (January-December for the RANN project and monthly from June-September for the Tip of the Mitt
      program</para>
    </samplingDescription>
   </sampling>
  </methods>
  <dataTable id="1350078968296">
   <entityName>Douglas_Lake_MI_secchi_longterm_EF.csv</entityName>
   <entityDescription>University of Michigan Biological Station: Research Applied to National Needs
    (RANN) , Tip of Mitt Watershed Council: Volunteer Lake Monitoring Program,
    1925-2011</entityDescription>
   <physical id="1350078719948">
    <objectName>Douglas_Lake_MI_secchi_longterm_EF.csv</objectName>
    <size unit="byte">60</size>
    <dataFormat>
     <textFormat>
      <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
      <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
      <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
      <simpleDelimited>
       <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
      </simpleDelimited>
     </textFormat>
    </dataFormat>
    <distribution>
     <offline>
      <mediumName>hard drive</mediumName>
     </offline>
    </distribution>
   </physical>
   <attributeList>
    <attribute id="1350078968297">
     <attributeName>Date</attributeName>
     <attributeLabel>Date</attributeLabel>
     <attributeDefinition>Date</attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="excel">Float</storageType>
     <measurementScale>
      <dateTime>
       <formatString>DD-MMM-YY</formatString>
      </dateTime>
     </measurementScale>
    </attribute>
    <attribute id="1350078968298">
     <attributeName>Secchi (m)</attributeName>
     <attributeLabel>Secchi, no view</attributeLabel>
     <attributeDefinition>Secchi depth</attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="excel">Float</storageType>
     <measurementScale>
      <ratio>
       <unit>
        <standardUnit>meter</standardUnit>
       </unit>
       <numericDomain>
        <numberType>real</numberType>
       </numericDomain>
      </ratio>
     </measurementScale>
    </attribute>
    <attribute id="1350078968299">
     <attributeName>Year</attributeName>
     <attributeLabel>Year</attributeLabel>
     <attributeDefinition>Year</attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="excel">Integer</storageType>
     <measurementScale>
      <dateTime>
       <formatString>YYYY</formatString>
      </dateTime>
     </measurementScale>
    </attribute>
    <attribute id="1350078968300">
     <attributeName>Secchi (ft)</attributeName>
     <attributeLabel>Secchi, no view</attributeLabel>
     <attributeDefinition>Secchi (ft)</attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="excel">float</storageType>
     <measurementScale>
      <ratio>
       <unit>
        <standardUnit>foot</standardUnit>
       </unit>
       <numericDomain>
        <numberType>real</numberType>
       </numericDomain>
      </ratio>
     </measurementScale>
    </attribute>
    <attribute id="1350078968301">
     <attributeName>Source</attributeName>
     <attributeLabel>Data source</attributeLabel>
     <attributeDefinition>Lists data source for observation</attributeDefinition>
     <storageType typeSystem="excel">text</storageType>
     <measurementScale>
      <nominal>
       <nonNumericDomain>
        <textDomain>
         <definition>Data source</definition>
        </textDomain>
       </nonNumericDomain>
      </nominal>
     </measurementScale>
    </attribute>
   </attributeList>
   <numberOfRecords>10</numberOfRecords>
  </dataTable>
 </dataset>
</eml:eml>
