<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:stmml="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml_1.1" packageId="edi.41.1" system="https://pasta.lternet.edu" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1  http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.1/eml.xsd">
  <access scope="document" order="allowFirst" authSystem="edi">
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=csmith,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset>
    <title>University of Rhode Island Watershed Watch (URIWW), RI: water quality monitoring, 1988-2010</title>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Elizabeth</givenName>
        <surName>Herron</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>University of Rhode Island Watershed Watch Program</organizationName>
      <positionName>URI Water Watch Program Coordinator</positionName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Rm 105 NRS - CIK</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>1 Greenhouse Rd.</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Kingston</city>
        <administrativeArea>RI</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>02881</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">401-874-4552</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>emh@uri.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <pubDate>2017-04-11</pubDate>
    <abstract>
      <para>The URI Watershed Watch (URIWW) is a volunteer water quality monitoring program that works with local communities to assess water quality. Led by trained scientists, URI Watershed Watch helps local governments, watershed, tribal and other organizations recruit and train volunteers to become citizen scientists gathering detailed, quality assured monitoring data. This watershed-based program focuses on long-term environmental monitoring of RI's fresh and salt water resources including lakes, ponds, streams and coastal waters. URIWW staff provides training, equipment, supplies and analytical services tailored to organizational needs, while meeting strict quality assurance and quality control guidelines in the field and in our state-certified water testing laboratory.
Sites included for LAGOS purposes are classified as Lakes by URIWW program.  Tidally-influenced or salt pond sites were excluded.   A single site was selected for the handful of lakes/reservoirs with 2 sampling site records, and a limited number of other lakes were excluded if they were sampled in only 1 year and for a subset of variables.  Otherwise, all sites classified as lakes by URIWW are included in the LAGOS-relevant files.</para>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>citizen monitoring</keyword>
      <keyword>inland lakes</keyword>
      <keyword>Rhode Island</keyword>
    </keywordSet>
    <intellectualRights>
      <para>
  This information is released to the public under the Creative Commons
  license CC0 1.0 Universal
  (https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/) and may be used
  for academic, educational, or commercial purposes subject to the
  following restrictions: The Data User must realize that these data
  sets are being actively used by others for ongoing research and that
  coordination may be necessary to prevent duplicate publication. The
  Data User is urged to contact the data creators or contacts. Where
  appropriate, the Data User may be encouraged to consider collaboration
  and/or co-authorship with original investigators. The Data User must
  realize that the data may be misinterpreted if taken out of context.
  The Data User must acknowledge use of the data by an appropriate
  citation (suggested format includes the DOI). While substantial
  efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation,
  complete accuracy of data sets cannot be guaranteed. All data are made
  available "as is". The creators shall not be liable for
  damages resulting from any use or misinterpretation of data sets. Data
  users should be aware that we periodically update data sets. By using
  these data, the Data User agrees to abide by the terms of this
  agreement. Thank you for your cooperation.
</para>
    </intellectualRights>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Inland lakes in Rhode Island, USA</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-71.58</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-71.08</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>42.0</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>41.17</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1988</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2010</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <contact>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Elizabeth</givenName>
        <surName>Herron</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>University of Rhode Island Watershed Watch Program</organizationName>
      <positionName>URI Water Watch Program Coordinator</positionName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Rm 105 NRS - CIK</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>1 Greenhouse Rd.</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Kingston</city>
        <administrativeArea>RI</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>02881</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">401-874-4552</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>emh@uri.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </contact>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <title>Alkalinity lab</title>
            <para>Titration Method (2320B,) low alkalinity procedure 4d, from 1995 Standard Methods for Analysis of Wastewater. The MDL is 0 mg/L.  Alkalinity of a sample may be reported as 0 mg/L when the initial pH of the sample is at or below the titration endpoint of 4.5 SU.  The RL is set at 0.1 mg/L.  Data are reported to 1 decimal place.   *Some negative values are also reported in their data</para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <title>Chloride lab</title>
            <para>Samples are filtered and then analyzed on an autoanalyzer using a colorimetric technique to determine chloride concentration.  This method is appropriate for undiluted samples ranging from less than 5 to 50 mg/L Cl and samples diluted to return values in this range.  Astoria-Pacific Model 303a  autoanalyzer .  - Chloride (4500-Cl-) and Automated Ferricyanide Method (4500-Cl- E).  The MDL for this assay is determined annually and has been 0.3 mg/L chloride (Cl) or less. The RL for this assay is 3 mg/L Cl- or lower. The upper limit of reporting is 50 mg/L Cl- without dilution and is set by the upper standard.  Results are reported to the nearest whole number.  Updated MDL and RL values are calculated on an annual basis.</para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <title>Chlorophyll a</title>
            <para>samples either filtered (all type A/E glass fiber filter) in the field or immediately upon arrival in the lab; filters are frozen until extraction in buffered acetone and analysis via fluorometer.  Standard Methods (1995) # Chlorophyll (10200 H).  The MDL is 1.0 µg/L chlorophyll-a as read on the fluorometer.  This is equivalent to 0.1 µg/L chlorophyll-a in a 50 mL aliquot of water.  The reporting limit (RL) is 2.0 µg/L chlorophyll-a as read on the fluorometer; equivalent to 0.2 µg/L chlorophyll-a in a 50 mL  aliquot of water.  The upper RL is 50 µg/L chlorophyll-a for the normal calibration and 100 µg/L chlorophyll-a for a high level calibration, assuming no dilution of the sample.  Data are reported to 1 decimal place.   Some time between 2001 and 2002, there was a method change from “Analog” to “Digital”, as reported in URIWW files, presumably indicating an upgrade in the fluorometer being used in this analysis.  All data prior to 2002 is analog.  All data from 2002 forward is digital.  Some parallel analyses were done in 2001 for these two methods, and showed little difference between methods.</para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <title>NH4 lab</title>
            <para>Automated phenate method on Astoria Pacific autoanalyzer.  Method referenced:  Nitrogen (Ammonia) 4500-NH4 G.  The MDL is set at 3.0 µg/L NH3-N.  The RL is set at 30 µg/L NH3-N.  The maximum concentration reported without dilution is 2000 µg/L NH3-N for ISDS samples and 1000 µg/L NH3-N for ambient and marine samples, based on the highest calibration standard.  Values reported for NH3-N are reported to the nearest 10 (ie: 152 µg/L NH3-N is reported as 150 µg/L NH3-N and 66 µg/L NH3-N is reported as 70 µg/L NH3-N).  Updated MDL and RL values are calculated on an annual basis.</para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <title>NO3 lab</title>
            <para>Automated Cadmium Reduction (4500-NO3 – F) using an Astoria-Pacific Model 303A segmented flow autoanalyzer. The maximum concentration reported by the nitrate + nitrite assay without dilution is 2000 μg/L NO3/NO2-N for all samples The MDL is set at 2.3 µgN/L and the RL at 23 µgN/L. Values reported for NO3/NO2-N are reported to the nearest 10’s (ie: 126 μg/L NO3/NO2-N is reported as 130 μg/L NO3/NO2-N).</para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <title>TP lab</title>
            <para>unfiltered samples, and analyzed together via potassium persulfate digestion followed by PO4/NO3 analysis on Astoria-Pacific autoanalyzer.</para>
            <para>Ameel, J.J., R.P. Axler, and C.J. Owen. 1993. Persulfate Digestion for Determination of Total Nitrogen and Total Phosphorus in Low-Nutrient Waters. American Laboratory.</para>
            <para>TP- Automated Ascorbic Acid Reduction Method (Section 4500-P F. Phosphorus).</para>
            <para>The MDL is set at 0.3 μg/L P for the total phosphorus assay</para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <title>TN lab</title>
            <para>unfiltered samples, and analyzed together via potassium persulfate digestion followed by PO4/NO3 analysis on Astoria-Pacific autoanalyzer.</para>
            <para>Ameel, J.J., R.P. Axler, and C.J. Owen. 1993. Persulfate Digestion for Determination of Total Nitrogen and Total Phosphorus in Low-Nutrient Waters. American Laboratory.</para>
            <para>Persulfate Method with automated cadmium reduction (Section 4500-Norg. D).</para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <title>pH lab</title>
            <para>measured using a pH meter in the lab on an unfiltered water sample- Electrometric Method (4500-H+ B) from 1995 Standard Methods for Analysis of Wastewater.  The MDL for the pH is 1.00 SU (lower) and  14.00 SU (upper)  The reporting limit (RL) for the pH assay is 1.0 SU and the upper RL is 14.0 SU  Data are reported to 1 decimal place. The meter used in this SOP reports pH values to 0.01 SU</para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <title>Secchi field</title>
            <para>average of 1-5 measurements made between 10 a.m. and 2 p.m. from th sunny side of the boat without a viewer. +/- 0.1 m</para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <title>Temperature</title>
            <para>measured with a thermometer placed in a filled 1-L bottle usually collected at 1-m.  On most dates, values reported to the nearest whole degree C.</para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <title>QA/QC</title>
            <para>US EPA and RI Department of Environmental Management approved quality assurance project plans (QAPP) in pdf. The documents labels QAPP include the main document with the actual procedures in the SOPs and are rigorous.  However, methods histories are unknown, and it is highly likely that methods and QA/QC procedures  have changed over the 20+ year program.</para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <sampling>
        <studyExtent>
          <description>
            <para>Lakes and ponds throughout the state are included in this data set</para>
          </description>
        </studyExtent>
        <samplingDescription>
          <para>The RI Water Watch program began with 15 sites in 1988 and is ongoing and includes &gt;125 sites.  Sampling within and across years and across sites has been highly erratic.  For most years, sampling occurred on spring, summer, and fall months, with frequency of sampling increasing to monthly from spring – fall in 2008 or 2009.  However, there are many exceptions, including both more frequent (rare) and less frequent (common) sampling.

Sampling is done at the deepest point within individual ponds/lakes, typically at a depth of 1 m, although there is a small number of exceptions in which samples and measurements were taken at 0.5 m (e.g., for shallow sites), and a few cases in which measurements may have been made/taken at 0.1 m, but without having specified the actual depth in the original data file.

Secchi depth and temperature are supposed to be measured weekly, chlorophyll every other week, and chemistry either seasonally or monthly.  However, there are many departures from this schedule.  Chemical variables measured (see below) are not always measured in all year.  2004 is a particularly sparse year, for example, with TP and Cl representing the only chemical measurements, and often only 1 or 2x/year per site.  Ca and Mg were analyzed in 1988-1992 then apparently discontinued, but are included in the data file.  Other variables measured for 1-2 years at the start of the Water Watch program include Na, SO4, VOCs.  NH4 was measured in 1988, but with high detection limits and was discontinued until 1998-9.  TN measurements began in 1993.  Excluded variables present in most years included bacteria (e.g., E. coli),dissolved oxygen, and dissolved P.</para>
        </samplingDescription>
      </sampling>
    </methods>
    <dataTable>
      <entityName>RI_URIWW_CHEM.csv</entityName>
      <entityDescription>University of Rhode Island Watershed Watch (URIWW), RI: water quality monitoring, 1988-2010</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>RI_URIWW_CHEM.csv</objectName>
        <size unit="bytes">1433098</size>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
              <quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url>https://lter.limnology.wisc.edu/sites/default/files/data/LAGOS_NE_LIMNO_RAWDATA/RI_URIWW_CHEM/RI_URIWW_CHEM.csv</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>WB_Code</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>unique lake identifier</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>unique lake identifier</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Site</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Note that there is substantial non-uniqueness in this field. Some sites share the same name, and many sites have multiple names (or- a name used in early years of surveying was replaced by another name later on).</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Note that there is substantial non-uniqueness in this field. Some sites share the same name, and many sites have multiple names (or- a name used in early years of surveying was replaced by another name later on).</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Date</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Date</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>date</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>mm/dd/yyyy</formatString>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Alk</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Alkalinity</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>milligramsPerLiter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Cl</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Chloride (milligramsPerLiter)</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Chloride (milligramsPerLiter)</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Chl_a</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Chlorophyll a</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>microgramsPerLiter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>NH4</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Nitrogen, NH4 (microgramsPerLiter)</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Nitrogen, NH4 (microgramsPerLiter)</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>NO3</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Nitrogen, nitrite (NO2) + nitrate (NO3) (microgramsPerLiter)</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Nitrogen, nitrite (NO2) + nitrate (NO3) (microgramsPerLiter)</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>TN</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Nitrogen, total</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>microgramsPerLiter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>pH</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>pH</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>TP</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Phosphorus, total (microgramsPerLiter)</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Phosphorus, total (microgramsPerLiter)</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Secchi</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Secchi</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>meter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Temp</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Temperature</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>celsius</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Ca</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Calcium</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>milligramsPerLiter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Mg</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Magnesium</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>milligramsPerLiter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
    </dataTable>
    <otherEntity>
      <entityName>DataImport_RI_URIWW_CHEM.R</entityName>
      <entityDescription>Imports data for the LAke multi-scaled GeOSpatial database (LAGOS)</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>DataImport_RI_URIWW_CHEM.R</objectName>
        <size unit="bytes">22356</size>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>0</numHeaderLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter></fieldDelimiter>
              <quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url>https://lter.limnology.wisc.edu/sites/default/files/data/LAGOS_NE_LIMNO_RAWDATA/RI_URIWW_CHEM/DataImport_RI_URIWW_CHEM.R</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <entityType>R code</entityType>
    </otherEntity>
  </dataset>
</eml:eml>