<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<eml:eml xmlns:eml="https://eml.ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:stmml="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.2" packageId="edi.514.2" xsi:schemaLocation="https://eml.ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0  https://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.2.0/xsd/eml.xsd" system="edi">
  <access authSystem="https://pasta.edirepository.org/authentication" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=edi,o=EDI,dc=edirepository,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset>
    <title>Mechanisms influencing physically sequestered soil carbon in temperate restored grasslands in South Africa and North America</title>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Drew</givenName>
        <givenName>A</givenName>
        <surName>Scott</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Southern Illinois University</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>dascott@siu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0361-9522</userId>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Elizabeth</givenName>
        <givenName>M</givenName>
        <surName>Bach</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Nachusa Grasslands</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>elizabeth.bach@tnc.org</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Chris</givenName>
        <givenName>C</givenName>
        <surName>Du Preez</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>University of the Free State</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>dPreezCC@ufs.ac.za</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Johan</givenName>
        <surName>Six</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>ETH Zurich</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>jsix@ethz.ch</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Sara</givenName>
        <givenName>G</givenName>
        <surName>Baer</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>University of Kansas</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>sgbaer@ku.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <pubDate>2020-09-28</pubDate>
    <abstract>
      <para>This dataset contains a measurement of physically protected carbon (microaggregate-within-macroaggregate C) and potential drivers of physically protected C accumulation during grassland restoration. The data were collected from three independent grassland restorations from agriculture in North America and South Africa. Northeast Kansas, USA data were collected in May 2013. Northeast Free State, RSA data were collected in September–November 2005. Southeast Nebraska, USA data were collected in October 2008–May 2008. Aggregate fractionations were performed by hierarchical wet sieving (Six et al 2000). Carbon and N quantification were done by flash combustion-gas chromatography. Microbial biomass C quantification was performed with chloroform fumigation-incubation (chloroform fumigation-extraction in the case of northeast Kansas). Phospholipid fatty acid biomass analysis was conducted using the methods of Bligh and Dyer (1959).</para>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>Arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi</keyword>
      <keyword>Conservation Reserve Program</keyword>
      <keyword>Microaggregate-within-macroaggregate</keyword>
      <keyword>Microbial biomass</keyword>
      <keyword>Roots</keyword>
      <keyword>Soil organic matter</keyword>
      <keyword>Soil structure</keyword>
    </keywordSet>
    <intellectualRights>
      <para>This information is released under the Creative Commons license - Attribution - CC BY (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). The consumer of these data (\"Data User\" herein) is required to cite it appropriately in any publication that results from its use. The Data User should realize that these data may be actively used by others for ongoing research and that coordination may be necessary to prevent duplicate publication. The Data User is urged to contact the authors of these data if any questions about methodology or results occur. Where appropriate, the Data User is encouraged to consider collaboration or co-authorship with the authors. The Data User should realize that misinterpretation of data may occur if used out of context of the original study. While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and associated documentation, complete accuracy of data sets cannot be guaranteed. All data are made available \"as is.\" The Data User should be aware, however, that data are updated periodically and it is the responsibility of the Data User to check for new versions of the data. The data authors and the repository where these data were obtained shall not be liable for damages resulting from any use or misinterpretation of the data. Thank you.
</para>
    </intellectualRights>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Northeast Kansas, USA sites</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-96.58333</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-96.58333</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>39.08333</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>39.08333</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Gage, Southeast Nebraska, USA</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-96.69347</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-96.69347</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>40.26508</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>40.26508</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Northeast Free State, South Africa</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>29.18333</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>29.18333</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>-28.2</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>-28.2</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Saline,  Southeast Nebraska, USA</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-97.14231</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-97.14231</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>40.53134</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>40.53134</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>2005-09-01</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2013-05-31</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <maintenance>
      <description>completed</description>
    </maintenance>
    <contact>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Drew</givenName>
        <givenName>A</givenName>
        <surName>Scott</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Southern Illinois University</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>dascott@siu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0361-9522</userId>
    </contact>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>Site Descriptions</para>
          <para>All chronosequences used in this analysis were selected based on the criteria that sites had been cultivated long enough to achieve a new (lower) equilibrium C stocks (Baer et al. 2015), were planted to perennial C4 grasses, and contained at least 9% clay, as grassland restored on soil with little to no clay content does not accrue C on a decadal time scale (Baer et al. 2010). </para>
          <para>The southeast Nebraska site consisted of 22 independent restorations that were part of the Unites States Department of Agriculture’s Conservation Reserve Program, with ages ranging from 4–19 years restored. These restorations were on silty clay loam (Fine smectitic, mesic Aquertic Argiudolls) soils formed by loess with 0–6% slope. Crop rotations in this area often include corn, wheat, oat, soy, and sorghum. Most of these fields were restored by sowing equal amounts of 6 grass species (Andropogon gerardii Vitman, Schizachyrium scoparium (Michx.) Nash, Panicum virgatum L., Pascopyrum smithii (Rydb.) Á. Löve, Bouteloua curtipendula (Michx.) Torr., and Sorghastrum nutans (L.) Nash). This region had a mean annual temperature of 10.9° C of and a mean annual precipitation of 757 mm. Baer et al. (2010) and Bach et al. (2010) provide a detailed description of the fields sampled in this chronosequence.  </para>
          <para>The northeast Kansas site consisted of 6 independent restorations, with ages ranging from 1–35 years restored. These restorations were on Reading silt loam (fine silt, mixed, superactive, mesic Pachic Argiudoll) soils formed from alluvial silt deposits and Clime silty clay loam (fine, mixed, active, mesic Udothentic Haplustolls)– Sogn silt loam complex (loamy, mixed, superactive, mesic Lithic Haplustolls) soils formed from residuum from shale and limestone respectively. Sampled areas had less than 5% slope. These fields were in cultivation for 50 or more years prior to restoration. Crop rotations in this area often include corn, soy, sorghum, and winter wheat. These fields were restored by sowing a variety of seed mixes. The most commonly encountered plant species were Andropogon gerardii Vitman, Sorghastrum nutans (L.) Nash, and Lespedeza capitate Michx. This site had a mean annual temperature of 12.7° C of and a mean annual precipitation of 833 mm. Scott et al. (2017) provide a detailed description of the fields sampled in this chronosequence.        	</para>
          <para>The northeast Free State site consisted of 17 independent restorations near Harrismith, with ages ranging from 4–44 years restored. These restorations were on fine loamy sand to fine sandy loam, thermic, mixed Typic Plinthustalfs soils with less than 5% slope. The fields were in cultivation for 30 or more years before restoration. Crop rotations in this area often include fallow, wheat, corn, and sunflower. Most fields were restored by sowing Eragrostis curvula (Schrad.) Nees. This site had a mean annual temperature of 13.8° C of and a mean annual precipitation of 635 mm. Baer et al. (2015) provide a detailed description of the fields sampled in this chronosequence.</para>
          <para>Measurements</para>
          <para>&#13;
We used measurements of root biomass, root C:N ratio, bulk density, percent of macroaggregates by whole soil mass, percent of microaggregate-within-macroaggregates by combined macroaggregate mass, microbial biomass C, total PLFA biomass, PLFA fungi:bacteria ratio, and microaggregate-within-macroaggregate C from the perennial grassland restoration chronosequences in southeast Nebraska, USA (SENE) (Bach et al. 2010; Baer et al. 2010), northeast Free State, RSA (NEFS) (Baer et al. 2015), and northeast Kansas, USA (NEKS) (Scott et al. 2017). All data were produced using the same methods, with the exception of sample depth increments. Data from Scott et al. (2017) and Baer et al. (2010) were derived from 0-10 cm soil depth. Data from Baer et al. (2015) collected in NEFS were derived from the 0-5 cm and 5-10 cm depth. The sequestered soil carbon (represented by the microaggregate-within-macroaggregate fraction) were not previously reported for the SENE and NEFS studies. </para>
          <para>At all sites, intact soil cores (5 cm dia.) were removed and stored at 4oC until processed (within one week of sampling). In the laboratory, each core was broken along planes of natural weakness and passed through an 8 mm sieve. Roots were then removed with forceps, washed with deionized water and dried (60°C) to determine root biomass. Dried roots were ground to a fine powder and 5-10 g of soil was analyzed for %C and %N by dry combustion followed by gas chromatography on a CN Analyzer (Thermo Scientific, New Brunswick, NJ USA). A subsample of freshly sieved soil (~20 g) was used to determine gravimetric water content and back-calculate bulk density based on the volume and dry weight of soil. Another subsample of freshly sieved soil (30 mL) was frozen in a falcon tube and later used for PLFA analyses. A subsample of ~100 g was air dried and used for aggregate fractionation. </para>
          <para>Phospholipid fatty acid biomarkers were extracted from soils using a chloroform extraction (Bligh and Dyer 1959; Bossio et al. 1998; DeGrood et al. 2005). Solid phase extraction was used to separate the neutral- and glycolipids from the phospholipids. Fatty acid methyl esters were dissolved in hexane and analyzed with gas chromatography. See previous publications for full details (SENE: Baer et al. 2010; Bach et al. 2010; NEFS: Baer et al. 2015; NEKS: Scott et al. 2017).   </para>
          <para>A hierarchical wet-sieving method was used to fractionate soil into aggregate classes and further isolate microaggregates-within-macroaggregates according to Six et al. (2000 a and b). Soil passing through an 8 mm sieve was air dried before slaking and isolating aggregates (&gt;2 mm: macroaggregates; &lt;2 mm and &gt;250 μm: small macroaggregates; &lt;250 μm and &gt;50 μm: microaggregates; and &lt; 50 μm: silt and clay). Macroaggregates were dried at 60° C and then shaken in water on a fine mesh with 50 4-mm ball bearings. The mesh isolated particulate organic matter within the macroaggregates. The water was then poured over a 50 m sieve to isolate microaggregates within the macroaggregates. This fraction was dried at a low temperature (60° C), then analyzed for %C and %N using the same methods described for root biomass. Carbon stocks for this fraction and bulk soil (total C stocks) were calculated using minimum equivalent mass. In the case of NEKS total C stocks were calculated as the sum of C in aggregate fractions. See previous publications for full details (SENE: Baer et al. 2010; Bach et al. 2010; NEFS: Baer et al. 2015; NEKS: Scott et al. 2017).  &#13;
</para>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <dataTable>
      <entityName>physically protected carbon</entityName>
      <entityDescription>Data from three sites (southeast Nebraska, USA; northeast Kansas, USA; northeast Free State, South Africa) were synthesized. Data were used to create a mixed model regression of microaggregate-within-macroaggregate carbon increase with age among all site, with site as a random effect. Data were also used to fit structural equation models explaining predominant mechanism of microaggregate-within-macroaggregate carbon accumulation in each site and all combined sites.</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>micro_within_macro_synthesis.csv</objectName>
        <size unit="bytes">3500</size>
        <authentication method="MD5">2fd43948d99372eedccffacb9b8a29ea</authentication>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
              <quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
      </physical>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Location</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Region where restoration chronosequence was located</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Region where restoration chronosequence was located</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Site</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Researchers’ name for each site</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Researchers’ name for each site</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>age</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Restoration age with first growing season of restoration counting as 1 year</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>natural</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">1</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">44</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>not available</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>depth</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>depth of soil profile used in structural equation model analyses in centimeter ranges</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>depth of soil profile used in structural equation model analyses in centimeter ranges</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>RootBiomass</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>biomass of roots; no attempt was made to distinguish live and dead roots</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>gramsPerSquareMeter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">23.73</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">688.24</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>not available</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>RootQuality</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Root C:N ratio</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">31.68</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">101.07</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>not available</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>MBC</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Microbial biomass carbon using chloroform fumigation-incubation (chloroform incubation-extraction in the case of NEKS)</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>microgramsPerGram</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">25.04</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">886.78</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>not available</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>PLFAbiomass</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Total phospholipid fatty acid biomarker (PLFA) biomass</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>nanomolesPerGram</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">10.47</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">86.96</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>not available</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>FungiBacteria</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Fungi PLFA biomass:bacteria PLFA biomass ratio</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">0.19</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">0.44</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>not available</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>AMF</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi PLFA biomass</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>nanomolesPerGram</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">0.35</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">7.09</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>not available</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Macros</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Percentage of macroaggregates by mass</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">33.41</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">91.85</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>not available</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>BulkDensity</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Bulk density using calculated from gravimetric water content and assuming a mineral soil particle density of 2.65 g cm-3</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>gramsPerCubicCentimeter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">1.1</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">1.73</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>not available</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>iMicros</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Percentage of microaggregates-within-macroaggregates by mass</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">36.04</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">86.21</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>not available</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>SoilC</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Minimum equivalent mass (for a site) soil carbon</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>gramsPerSquareMeter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">156.26</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">1326.4</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>not available</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>SoilC10</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Minimum equivalent mass (for a site) soil carbon for a 10 cm soil profile</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>gramsPerSquareMeter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">267.63</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">1516.1</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>not available</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Clay</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Percent clay content from a hydrometer soil texture analysis</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>natural</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">9</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">39</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>not available</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
      <numberOfRecords>36</numberOfRecords>
    </dataTable>
    <otherEntity>
      <entityName>Biogeochemistry 2020 code.R</entityName>
      <entityDescription>Code for linear mixed models, structural equation models, and linear models with estimated marginal means</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>Biogeochemistry 2020 code.R</objectName>
        <size unit="bytes">5961</size>
        <authentication method="MD5">e9b8d9d2f41aa47adec6fbc2f3830cdf</authentication>
        <dataFormat>
          <externallyDefinedFormat>
            <formatName>text/plain</formatName>
          </externallyDefinedFormat>
        </dataFormat>
      </physical>
      <entityType>unknown</entityType>
    </otherEntity>
  </dataset>
  <additionalMetadata>
    <metadata>
      <unitList>
        <unit id="nanomolesPerGram" multiplierToSI="" name="nanomolesPerGram" parentSI="" unitType="">
          <description/>
        </unit>
      </unitList>
    </metadata>
  </additionalMetadata>
</eml:eml>
