<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<eml:eml xmlns:eml="https://eml.ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:stmml="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.2" packageId="edi.529.1" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0  https://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.2.0/xsd/eml.xsd" system="edi">
  <access authSystem="https://pasta.edirepository.org/authentication" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=edi,o=EDI,dc=edirepository,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset>
    <title>Data for study Conventional land-use intensification reduces species richness and increases production: A global meta-analysis</title>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Michael</givenName>
        <surName>Beckmann</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Department Computational Landscape Ecology, UFZ – Helmholtz Centre for Environmental Research, Leipzig, Germany</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>michael.beckmann@ufz.de</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5678-265X</userId>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Katharina</givenName>
        <surName>Gerstner</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>iDiv – German Centre for Integrative Biodiversity Research, Leipzig, Germany</organizationName>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0348-9334</userId>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Morodoluwa</givenName>
        <surName>Akin-Fajiye</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Department of Ecology and Evolution, Stony Brook University, Stony Brook, New York, USA</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>morodoluwa.akin-fajiye@stonybrook.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8078-3970</userId>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Silvia</givenName>
        <surName>Ceausu</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Center for Biodiversity Dynamics in a Changing World (BIOCHANGE), Aarhus University, Aarhus C, Denmark</organizationName>
      <organizationName>Section for Ecoinformatics and Biodiversity, Department of Bioscience, Aarhus University, Aarhus C, Denmark</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>silvia.ceausu@bios.au.dk</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6278-6075</userId>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Stephan</givenName>
        <surName>Kambach</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>iDiv – German Centre for Integrative Biodiversity Research, Leipzig, Germany</organizationName>
      <organizationName>Leipzip University, Leipzig, Germany</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>stephan.kambach@ufz.de</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Nicole</givenName>
        <givenName>L.</givenName>
        <surName>Kinlock</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Department of Ecology and Evolution, Stony Brook University, Stony Brook, New York, 11794, USA</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>nicole.kinlock@stonybrook.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2917-5133</userId>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Helen</givenName>
        <givenName>R.P.</givenName>
        <surName>Phillips</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>iDiv – German Centre for Integrative Biodiversity Research, Leipzig, Germany</organizationName>
      <organizationName>Leipzip University, Leipzig, Germany</organizationName>
      <organizationName>Department of Life Sciences, Imperial College, London, UK</organizationName>
      <organizationName>Department of Life Sciences, Natural History Museum, London, UK</organizationName>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7435-5934</userId>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Willem</givenName>
        <surName>Verhagen</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Environmental Geography Group, Institute for Environmental Studies, Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam, Amsterdam, The Netherlands</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>willem.verhagen@pbl.nl</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9394-0741</userId>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Jessica</givenName>
        <surName>Gurevitch</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Department of Ecology and Evolution, Stony Brook University, Stony Brook, New York, 11794, USA</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>jessica.gurevitch@stonybrook.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0157-4332</userId>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Stefan</givenName>
        <surName>Klotz</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Department of Community Ecology, UFZ – Helmholtz Centre for Environmental Research, Halle (Saale), Germany</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>stefan.klotz@ufz.de</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4355-6415</userId>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Tim</givenName>
        <surName>Newbold</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>United Nations Environment Programme World Conservation Monitoring Centre, Cambridge, United Kingdom</organizationName>
      <organizationName>Centre for Biodiversity and Environment Research, Department of Genetics, Evolution and Environment, University College London, London, United Kingdom</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>t.newbold@ucl.ac.uk</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7361-0051</userId>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Peter</givenName>
        <givenName>H.</givenName>
        <surName>Verburg</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Environmental Geography Group, Institute for Environmental Studies, Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam, Amsterdam, The Netherlands</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>p.h.verburg@vu.nl</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6977-7104</userId>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Martin</givenName>
        <surName>Winter</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>iDiv – German Centre for Integrative Biodiversity Research, Leipzig, Germany</organizationName>
      <organizationName>Leipzip University, Leipzig, Germany</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>marten.winter@idiv.de</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9593-7300</userId>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Ralf</givenName>
        <surName>Seppelt</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Department Computational Landscape Ecology, UFZ – Helmholtz Centre for Environmental Research, Leipzig, Germany</organizationName>
      <organizationName>Institute of Geoscience &amp; Geography, Martin-Luther-University Halle-Wittenberg, Halle (Saale), Germany</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>ralf.seppelt@ufz.de</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2723-7150</userId>
    </creator>
    <pubDate>2020-06-03</pubDate>
    <abstract>
      <para>
  Most current research on land‐use intensification addresses its
  potential to either threaten biodiversity or to boost agricultural
  production. However, little is known about the simultaneous effects of
  intensification on biodiversity and yield. To determine the responses
  of species richness and yield to conventional intensification, this
  dataset was created and a global meta‐analysis on it was carried out,
  thus synthesizing 115 studies. The dataset consists of 449 cases that
  cover a variety of areas used for agricultural (crops, fodder) and
  silvicultural (wood) production. It was found that across all
  production systems and species groups, conventional intensification is
  successful in increasing yield (grand mean + 20.3%), but it also
  results in a loss of species richness (−8.9%). However, analysis of
  sub‐groups revealed inconsistent results. Within high‐intensity
  systems species losses were non‐significant but yield gains were
  substantial (+15.2%). Conventional intensification within medium
  intensity systems revealed the highest yield increase (+84.9%) and
  showed the largest loss in species richness (−22.9%). Production
  systems differed in their magnitude of richness response, with
  insignificant changes in silvicultural systems and substantial losses
  in crop systems (−21.2%). In addition, this meta‐analysis identifies a
  lack of studies that collect robust biodiversity (i.e. beyond species
  richness) and yield data at the same sites and that provide
  quantitative information on land‐use intensity. These findings suggest
  that, in many cases, conventional land‐use intensification drives a
  trade‐off between species richness and production. However, species
  richness losses were often not significantly different from zero,
  suggesting even conventional intensification can result in yield
  increases without coming at the expense of biodiversity loss. These
  results, which were published in a paper titled Conventional land‐use
  intensification reduces species richness and increases production: A
  global meta‐analysis, could guide future research to close existing
  research gaps, and to understand the circumstances required to achieve
  such win‐win or win‐no‐harm situations in conventional agriculture.
</para>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>Land use</keyword>
      <keyword>meta-analysis</keyword>
    </keywordSet>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>land use history</keyword>
      <keyword>biodiversity</keyword>
      <keyword>species richness</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <intellectualRights>
      <para>
  This information is released under the Creative Commons license -
  Attribution - CC BY (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).
  The consumer of these data ("Data User" herein) is required
  to cite it appropriately in any publication that results from its use.
  The Data User should realize that these data may be actively used by
  others for ongoing research and that coordination may be necessary to
  prevent duplicate publication. The Data User is urged to contact the
  authors of these data if any questions about methodology or results
  occur. Where appropriate, the Data User is encouraged to consider
  collaboration or co-authorship with the authors. The Data User should
  realize that misinterpretation of data may occur if used out of
  context of the original study. While substantial efforts are made to
  ensure the accuracy of data and associated documentation, complete
  accuracy of data sets cannot be guaranteed. All data are made
  available "as is." The Data User should be aware, however,
  that data are updated periodically and it is the responsibility of the
  Data User to check for new versions of the data. The data authors and
  the repository where these data were obtained shall not be liable for
  damages resulting from any use or misinterpretation of the data. Thank
  you.
</para>
    </intellectualRights>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Global</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-122.4175</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>175.25</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>68.416667</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>-37.8</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1994</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2019</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <maintenance>
      <description>completed</description>
    </maintenance>
    <contact>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Jessica</givenName>
        <surName>Gurevitch</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Department of Ecology and Evolution, Stony Brook University, Stony Brook, New York, 11794, USA</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>jessica.gurevitch@stonybrook.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0157-4332</userId>
    </contact>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>The fully formatted methods are attached as pdf</description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
          <title>
  Literature search and screening protocol
</title>
          <para>
  A systematic review in compliance with the Preferred Reporting Items
  for Systematic Reviews and Meta‐Analyses (PRISMA) framework (Moher,
  2009). A search was carried out on the Web of Science database for
  search terms related to land use, biodiversity and yield (see below
  for the full search term and all refinement options employed). All
  articles published since 1 January 1990 in English or Spanish were
  included. The final search resulted in 9,909 studies.
</para>
          <para>
  Studies meeting the following selection criteria were included:
  Studies had to measure both species richness and yield in the same
  site in response to the application of conventional land‐use
  intensification. This included studies measuring the effect of
  conventional intensification on several sites in response to different
  intensities (i.e. space‐for‐time substitutes). Out of the full initial
  set of papers, astracts of 6,116 sudies were manually screened.
  Studies were retained only if they contained information about land
  use, species richness, and/or yield. In order to filter the remaining
  3,793 studies, a machine‐learning algorithm, based on ensembles of
  Support Vector Machines (SVMs), was used (developed for systematic
  reviews of the medical literature; see Wallace, Trikalinos, Lau,
  Brodley, &amp; Schmid, 2010). The machine‐learning algorithm correctly
  identified 84% of the manually screened studies as being relevant,
  with a specificity of 51% (standard deviation 0.016), that is, the
  model eliminated half of the irrelevant. The full text documents of
  all studies identified as potentially relevant (1,371), both screened
  manually or through machine learning, were acquired and processed
  further.
</para>
          </section>
          <section>
          <title>
  Data extraction and validation
</title>
          <para>
  From these 1,371 studies, 115 studies had sufficient data to be
  included. Means, standard deviations and sample sizes for control
  (lower land‐use intensity) and treatment (higher land‐use intensity)
  were extracted from the text, tables or figures (using ImageJ;
  Schneider, Rasband, &amp; Eliceiri, 2012). If data were not completely
  available in the main document and the Supplementary Material, it was
  request requested from the corresponding author. Studies that did not
  report means or sample sizes were excluded from the analysis. This
  resulted in a total of 115 studies that were used in subsequent
  analyses. Data coding and data review were undertaken by eight of the
  co‐authors. Initially, studies were coded as a group to assure
  inter‐coder consistency and reliability. Subsequently, frequent
  internal reviews were conducted to maintain consistency. Each document
  was coded by at least two of the co‐authors.
</para>
          <para>
  Only those studies were incorporated which included, both, information
  on species richness and yield in response to conventional land‐use
  intensification in the same locations. The measurements for both
  variables also had to be collected at the same area (but possibly in
  differently sized plots), excluding studies that, for example,
  measured species richness in plots or landscapes and used
  coarser‐scale statistics (e.g. sub‐national) for yield. It was assumed
  that the original study authors sampled yield and species richness
  using appropriate spatial units for both. Based on the type of product
  that was harvested the production system (crop, green fodder or wood)
  was first classified according to the description of the land use
  provided in the original paper.
</para></section>
          <section>
          <title>
  Land‐use intensity and intensification classification
</title>
          <para>
  The classification system for land‐use intensity was based on a
  pre‐defined set of management practices. Land‐use intensity was
  defined based on energy use and labor as a combination of input
  intensity (e.g. type of fertilizer/pesticide application) and aspects
  related to output or harvest intensity (e.g. type of harvest, number
  of harvests per year) but not the actual outputs (i.e. yields)
  themselves in order to avoid circularity. While this conceptualization
  of intensification will identify more intensive systems based on the
  type of management practices implemented (e.g. no fertilizer
  vs. organic vs. chemical fertilizer), it does not classify land‐use
  intensity based on quantities of a management practice (e.g. kg
  nitrogen applied per area). Thus, the classification of
  intensification best reflects conventional intensification, rather
  than other forms of intensification (e.g. sustainable intensification
  in agriculture; Rockström et al., 2017) and it also allows for
  comparisons across production systems and regions (Hudson et al.,
  2014).
</para>
          <para>
  For studying a gradient of land‐use intensification steps, first three
  broad land‐use intensity classes were defined: low, medium and high,
  with separate criteria for each of the globally most common production
  systems: crops, wood and green fodder(see Table 1). In a second step,
  we distinguished different degrees of conventional land‐use
  intensification within each study in order to form intensification
  cases for the subsequent analysis. Land‐use intensification could
  occur in small steps, meaning an increase in pre‐existing management
  activities that does not lead to substantial changes in the production
  system (i.e. no change of land‐use intensity class). In this way,
  cases for the intensification steps low‐low, medium‐medium and
  high‐high were formed. More substantial changes in land‐use may lead
  to a change of a production system into another land‐use intensity
  class, resulting in cases covering the low‐medium, medium‐high and
  low‐high intensification steps.
</para>
          <para>
  By including measurements for different species groups and/or types of
  yield, a publication could provide several cases of land‐use
  intensification (e.g. one response of crop yield and the responses of
  plants, birds and insects to a given intensification step would result
  in three species richness cases and one yield case) leading to unequal
  numbers of cases for species richness and yield.
</para>
          <para>
  Case extraction from all 115 studies and based on different land‐use
  intensification steps, taxa or product types as described above,
  resulted in a total of 449 cases, 292 cases for species richness and
  157 for yield.
</para></section>
          <section>
          <title>
  Full Web of Science search term
</title>
          <para>
  TOPIC search term:
</para>
          <para>
  (( ( (land use OR land*use OR (*forest* AND (plantation OR
  silvicult* OR *cut* OR logg*)) OR agro*forest* OR
  field* OR farm* OR agricult* OR grassland* OR pasture*
  OR rangeland OR meadow* OR cropland OR fertiliz* OR pesticid*
  OR fungicid* OR herbicid* OR irriga* )
</para>
          <para>
  AND
</para>
          <para>
  (diversity OR species richness OR biodiversity OR (taxonomic AND
  richness) OR (abundance* AND species) OR even*ess OR shannon OR
  simpson )
</para>
          <para>
  (provisioning OR producti* OR food OR fodder OR feed OR fibre OR
  logg* OR fuel OR commodit* OR harvest* OR wood OR timber OR
  coffee OR cacao OR crop* OR yield* OR oil) )
</para>
          <para>
  NOT
</para>
          <para>
  (solar cell OR *polymer* OR genom* OR spectrum OR nano* OR
  *tpase* OR DNA OR brain OR semicond* OR receptor OR memory OR
  lymph* OR neuro* OR *electr* OR mitoch* OR *plankton
  OR optic* OR marrow OR methan* OR clone OR cloning OR
  protein* OR pharmac* OR RNA OR *blast* OR epithel* OR
  chromat* OR membra* OR coral OR Cell OR marine OR fish* OR
  prokaryo* OR ocean* OR *porou* OR cortex OR crystal OR
  marine OR aerosol* OR hydrolog* OR hexamer OR atom* OR
  molecule* OR oxida* OR dioxide OR enzyme* OR Bose-Einstein OR
  *catalyt* OR pacemak* OR mars OR galaxy OR *galact* OR
  diabet* OR pluto* OR cardi* OR cadmium OR arabidopsis OR
  sexual OR glacial OR calcium OR ligament OR soil organic carbon OR
  radiation OR gibberellin* OR 3D OR sensor* OR new species OR
  hominin OR coast* OR infect* OR meta-analys* OR transpiration
  OR scenario* OR projected OR soil-rock OR termite-fungus OR
  termitomyces OR pathogenicity OR panicle OR rainwater harvesting OR
  crown architecture OR xray OR tomography OR household OR recycling OR
  imaging OR during succession OR ball* OR root rot OR trichoderma
  harzianum OR isolation trails OR pot experiment OR cloud immersion OR
  pimp OR radioactive contamination OR Chernobyl OR radiocaesium OR
  ragweed OR bruise OR machine vision OR plasma OR insulin OR linoleic
  OR infest* OR galling OR glucosid* OR allel* OR blood OR
  radial OR poison* OR milk OR subsurface OR evapotranspiration OR
  phytotron OR CH4 OR inflow OR detergent OR styrox OR ewe OR p
  resorption OR bull* OR pig production OR wean* OR diarrhoea OR
  prototype OR energy waste OR group discussion OR computer runs OR
  land-classification strategies OR household OR interview OR flav*
  OR jena experiment ) ))
</para>
          <para>
  NOT in TITLE:
</para>
          <para>
  ((model* OR wastewater OR contamination OR equation OR groundwater
  OR coefficient OR pore OR learning OR innovation OR flux* OR
  niche* OR demograph* OR urban* OR rehabilitat* OR
  cognit* OR stress* OR knowledge OR therapy OR somatic OR mining
  OR mineral* OR tool OR simula* OR fan OR sprayer OR bench OR
  poverty OR an index OR a new index OR bureaucra* OR epidem* OR
  review* OR synthes* OR disease OR infect* OR School OR
  teach* OR MRI OR *informatic* OR radio* OR vector OR
  labor* OR power OR depression OR kitchen OR *remediat* OR
  cranium OR river OR lake OR burrow* OR litter OR *algebra* OR
  industry OR earthquake OR elephant OR radio* OR wheel OR rail OR
  thrust OR ray OR program OR account* OR perceiv* OR percept*
  OR incent* OR debate* OR future OR view OR female* OR
  male* OR greenhouse* OR xylem OR phloem OR hydroponic* OR
  endophy* OR math* OR signal* OR embryo* OR anatom* OR
  allelopath* OR opinion* OR capital* OR enterpris* OR
  compound* OR trout OR plastic OR discharg* OR advice OR
  stoichiometr* OR iodine OR involucr* OR N-15* OR mutualism OR
  wildfire* OR volatile OR emmission* OR climate zoning OR
  ordination OR ration OR slaughtered OR force OR break* OR
  protogynous OR out-crossed OR outcrossed OR comment* OR
  forecast* OR aquat* OR probability OR prediction))
</para>
          <para>
  NOT in PUBLICATION NAME:
</para>
          <para>
  (( PLANT DISEASE OR NUTRIENT CYCLING IN AGROECOSYSTEMS OR WEED
  TECHNOLOGY OR WEED TECHNOLOGY OR WEED RESEARCH OR SOIL SCIENCE SOCIETY
  OF AMERICA JOURNAL OR EURASIAN SOIL SCIENCE OR TREE PHYSIOLOGY OR
  TREES STRUCTURE AND FUNCTION OR CHEMOSPHERE OR TRANSACTIONS OF THE
  ASAE OR soil tillage OR Economic Botany OR trends in ecology OR
  opinions OR policy OR philosophical OR LAND USE POLICY))
</para>
          <para>
  Refined by:
</para>
          <para>
  Timespan=1990-2014
</para>
          <para>
  Search language=Auto
</para>
          <para>
  RESEARCH DOMAINS=( SCIENCE TECHNOLOGY ) AND [excluding] DOCUMENT
  TYPES=( ABSTRACT OR CORRECTION OR BIOGRAPHY OR MEETING OR BOOK OR
  OTHER OR BIBLIOGRAPHY OR REVIEW OR LETTER OR REPORT OR ART AND
  LITERATURE OR EDITORIAL OR NEWS OR CASE REPORT ) AND LANGUAGES=(
  ENGLISH ) AND [excluding] LANGUAGES=( SPANISH OR PORTUGUESE OR DANISH
  OR FRENCH OR CHINESE OR JAPANESE OR SLOVAK OR GERMAN OR CZECH OR
  AFRIKAANS OR SLOVENIAN OR ESTONIAN ) AND RESEARCH AREAS=(
  ENVIRONMENTAL SCIENCES ECOLOGY OR AGRICULTURE OR PLANT SCIENCES OR
  SCIENCE TECHNOLOGY OTHER TOPICS OR FORESTRY OR EVOLUTIONARY BIOLOGY OR
  BIODIVERSITY CONSERVATION OR LIFE SCIENCES BIOMEDICINE OTHER TOPICS )
  AND [excluding] RESEARCH AREAS=( CHEMISTRY OR MARINE FRESHWATER
  BIOLOGY OR MATERIALS SCIENCE OR ENGINEERING OR BIOCHEMISTRY MOLECULAR
  BIOLOGY OR GENETICS HEREDITY OR FOOD SCIENCE TECHNOLOGY OR WATER
  RESOURCES OR ZOOLOGY OR PHYSICS OR BIOTECHNOLOGY APPLIED MICROBIOLOGY
  OR METEOROLOGY ATMOSPHERIC SCIENCES OR GEOLOGY OR ENERGY FUELS OR
  OCEANOGRAPHY OR PHYSICAL GEOGRAPHY OR TOXICOLOGY OR BUSINESS ECONOMICS
  OR VETERINARY SCIENCES OR PUBLIC ENVIRONMENTAL OCCUPATIONAL HEALTH OR
  PHARMACOLOGY PHARMACY OR MICROBIOLOGY OR CELL BIOLOGY OR MATHEMATICAL
  COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY ) AND [excluding] RESEARCH AREAS=( BIOPHYSICS OR
  DEMOGRAPHY OR RADIOLOGY NUCLEAR MEDICINE MEDICAL IMAGING OR PSYCHOLOGY
  OR REPRODUCTIVE BIOLOGY OR ARCHITECTURE OR PHYSIOLOGY OR INFORMATION
  SCIENCE LIBRARY SCIENCE OR HISTORY PHILOSOPHY OF SCIENCE OR OPTICS OR
  MICROSCOPY OR DEVELOPMENTAL BIOLOGY OR ANATOMY MORPHOLOGY OR MINING
  MINERAL PROCESSING OR RESEARCH EXPERIMENTAL MEDICINE OR COMMUNICATION
  OR ENTOMOLOGY OR MYCOLOGY OR PATHOLOGY OR ANTHROPOLOGY OR
  INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS OR NEUROSCIENCES NEUROLOGY OR REMOTE SENSING
  OR SOCIAL SCIENCES OTHER TOPICS OR CONSTRUCTION BUILDING TECHNOLOGY OR
  PALEONTOLOGY OR NUCLEAR SCIENCE TECHNOLOGY OR INSTRUMENTS
  INSTRUMENTATION OR IMAGING SCIENCE PHOTOGRAPHIC TECHNOLOGY OR
  FISHERIES OR GENERAL INTERNAL MEDICINE OR GEOGRAPHY OR GOVERNMENT LAW
  OR PHILOSOPHY OR URBAN STUDIES OR ENDOCRINOLOGY METABOLISM OR SOCIAL
  ISSUES OR COMPUTER SCIENCE OR EDUCATION EDUCATIONAL RESEARCH OR
  IMMUNOLOGY OR SOCIOLOGY OR TRANSPORTATION OR ARTS HUMANITIES OTHER
  TOPICS OR PUBLIC ADMINISTRATION OR HISTORY OR LITERATURE OR
  MATHEMATICS )
</para></section>
          <section>
          <title>
  Table 1 | Characterization of land-use intensity classes. The land-use
  intensity classes low, medium and high were characterized separately
  for the three product groups crops, green fodder and wood. Land-use
  intensity was associated to a certain class based on core aspects of
  land-use (e.g. fertilizer application, grazing regime, species
  management). This was done separately for each product type. Land-use
  intensity Crops Green fodder Wood </title>
            <para>
  Low - Crops biological pest control, no fertilization rotational cultivation, possibly with fallow year,
  natural irrigation
</para>
          <para>
  Low - Green Fodder: biological pest control, no fertilization, low
  density grazing, no signs of overgrazing, occasional mowing, no
  addition/removal of species
</para>
          <para>
  Low - Wood: either combination of or low selective and partial logging,
  no fertilization, low levels of thinning, heterogeneous age structure,
  naturally developing forest, usually multiple species forest
</para>
          <para>
  Medium - Crops: targeted pesticides natural fertilization monocultures
  single harvest per year, occasional man-made irrigation
</para>
          <para>
  Medium - Green Fodder: targeted pesticides, natural fertilization, medium
  density grazing, no signs of overgrazing, regular mowing, some
  addition/removal of species
</para>
          <para>
  Medium - Wood: selective or partial logging in whole forest area,
  natural fertilizer, conventional thinning, removal of non-production
  trees/understorey, homogeneous age structure, managed natural
  forests/low intensity plantation forest
</para>
          <para>
  High - Green Fodder: non-targeted pesticides, chemical fertilization,
  high density grazing, signs of overgrazing, regular mowing, multiple
  harvest/year addition/removal of species, monocultures
</para>
          <para>
  High - Wood: clear cut, chemical fertilization, chemical thinning, very
  high levels of thinning, plantation of exotic species, homogenous
  age/species structure, removal of understorey
</para></section>
          <section>
          <title>
  Table 2 Description of data used in the analysis. Overview and
  meta-data of the variables either coded directly from the studies or
  extracted from external data sources and used in the analysis.
</title>
          <para>
  Study Case - Each study-case corresponds to a unique set of response
  statistics. Hence, a single study can include multiple cases if it
  reports on more than two land-use intensities, species groups, or
  products, or if it reports on several locations that differ in
  covariates, e.g. climate. </para>
            <para>
  Longitude/Latitude - The geographic location
  of a study either as directly reported by the authors or, if missing,
  georeferenced by the coders based on a location description.</para>
            <para>
  Intensification step - Level of baseline and increased land-use
  intensity class based on the classification given in table 1. The
  intensity classes low, medium and high were used to form pairs
  ([initial]-[final]) of intensification steps (low-low, low-medium,
  medium-medium, medium-high, high-high and low-high). 
  </para>
            <para>Species group -
  Broad class of species group, i.e. vertebrates, invertebrates, and
  plants. Product - Broad class of harvested product, i.e. crop, green
  fodder, and wood. </para>
            <para>
  Climate - Broad climate zone according to the
  Köppen-Geiger climate classification, i.e. polar, cold (continental),
  temperate, arid, and tropical. </para>
            <para>Land-use history - Broad class of time
  of first significant use (table 3), i.e. 5950 BC, 50 BC, 1450, 1950,
  after 1950. And categorized according to the major developments of
  agriculture. </para>
            <para>Dependency of yield and species richness measure - An
  indication of whether species richness and yield are measured from the
  same species group, in which case species richness and production are
  considered to be linked rather than independent.</para>
            <para>Dependency of
  intensity class and yield measure - An indication of whether land-use
  intensity step is based on yield, in which case yield is considered to
  be linked to intensity rather than independent. For example the
  harvesting technique in forest (e.g. clear cut, selective logging) is
  used to define the land-use intensity class and also determines the
  amount of extracted yield.
</para></section>
          <section>
          <title>
  Table 3 Overview of the five major stages of history land-use applied
  in the analysis. Numbers given in brackets are species richness/yield
  cases that fall within one of the land-use history classes.
</title>
          <para>
  Land use history class (including all cells with greater than 20% used
  area) Short characterization of land-use intensification World regions
  of main agricultural area expansion</para>
            <para>Origin of agriculture (Neolithic
  Revolution), until 5,950 B.C. (n=21/9) Domestication of the first main
  crops (emmer, einkorn, wheat, barley, peas, lentils, rice, etc.) and
  agricultural animals. The fertile crescent (Levante), China, New
  Guinea, Central and South America (Andean region)</para>
            <para>Expansion of
  agriculture, 5,950 B.C. - 50 B.C. (n=115/57) Significant enlargement
  of agriculture especially in Central and South America, and the Sahel
  region of Africa, new domesticated crops and animals, cotton in Peru,
  maize in Central America. Africa, Europe, Central and South America</para>
  <para>Middle Ages, 50 B.C. - 1.450 A.D. (n=35/23)Further enlargement of
  agriculture, especially in the temperate and boreal zone in the Old
  World Europe, Asia, Africa, Central and South America</para>
            <para>Modern
  agriculture, 1,450 - 1,950 A.D. (n=47/23) From first technological
  advances, (e.g. three-field system, exchange of Old World and New
  World crops, livestock exchange) to the first agricultural revolution
  (e.g. first machineries, four-field system, artificial fertilizers).
  Include the beginning of global industrialization of agriculture,
  broad use of mineral fertilizers and pesticides.</para>
            <para>Global Green
  Revolution, 1,950 - today (n= 74/36) New breeds in crops and
  livestock, genetically modified organism and new pesticides Global
</para></section>
          <section>
          <title>
  Literature used
</title>
          <para>
  Adekunle, V.A.J., Olagoke, A.O. &amp; Ogundare, L.F. (2013). Timber
  exploitation rate in tropical rainforest ecosystem of southwest
  Nigeria and its implications on sustainable forest management. Applied
  Ecology and Environmental Research, 11, 123–136
</para>
          <para>
  Annand, E.M. &amp; Thompson III, F.R. (1997). Forest bird response to
  regeneration practices in central hardwood forests. The Journal of
  Wildlife Management, 61, 159–171
</para>
          <para>
  Baker, M.D. &amp; Lacki, M.J. (1997). Short-term changes in bird
  communities in response to silvicultural prescriptions. Forest ecology
  and management, 96, 27–36
</para>
          <para>
  Batáry, P., Sutcliffe, L., Dormann, C.F. &amp; Tscharntke, T. (2013).
  Organic farming favours insect-pollinated over non-insect pollinated
  forbs in meadows and wheat fields. PloS one, 8, e54818
</para>
          <para>
  Battles, J.J., Shlisky, A.J., Barrett, R.H., Heald, R.C. &amp;
  Allen-Diaz, B.H. (2001). The effects of forest management on plant
  species diversity in a Sierran conifer forest. Forest ecology and
  management, 146, 211–222
</para>
          <para>
  Beltman, B., Willems, J.H. &amp; Güsewell, S. (2007). Flood events
  overrule fertiliser effects on biomass production and species richness
  in riverine grasslands. Journal of Vegetation Science, 18, 625–634
</para>
          <para>
  Boch, S., Prati, D., Hessenmöller, D., Schulze, E.-D. &amp; Fischer,
  M. (2013a). Richness of lichen species, especially of threatened ones,
  is promoted by management methods furthering stand continuity. PloS
  one, 8, e55461
</para>
          <para>
  Boch, S., Prati, D., Müller, J., Socher, S., Baumbach, H., Buscot, F.,
  et al. (2013b). High plant species richness indicates
  management-related disturbances rather than the conservation status of
  forests. Basic and applied ecology, 14, 496–505
</para>
          <para>
  Boncina, A., Kadunc, A. &amp; Robic, D. (2007). Effects of selective
  thinning on growth and development of beech (Fagus sylvatica L.)
  forest stands in south-eastern Slovenia. Annals of forest science, 64,
  47–57
</para>
          <para>
  Boreux, V., Kushalappa, C.G., Vaast, P. &amp; Ghazoul, J. (2013).
  Interactive effects among ecosystem services and management practices
  on crop production: pollination in coffee agroforestry systems.
  Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 110, 8387–8392
</para>
          <para>
  Boström, U. &amp; Fogelfors, H. (2002). Long-term effects of
  herbicide-application strategies on weeds and yield in spring-sown
  cereals. Weed science, 50, 196–203
</para>
          <para>
  Boström, U. &amp; Fogelfors, H. akan. (1999). Type and time of autumn
  tillage with and without herbicides at reduced rates in southern
  Sweden: 2. Weed flora and diversity. Soil and Tillage Research, 50,
  283–293
</para>
          <para>
  Campiglia, E., Radicetti, E. &amp; Mancinelli, R. (2012). Weed control
  strategies and yield response in a pepper crop (Capsicum annuum L.)
  mulched with hairy vetch (Vicia villosa Roth.) and oat (Avena sativa
  L.) residues. Crop Protection, 33, 65–73
</para>
          <para>
  Chen, J., Yamamura, Y., Hori, Y., Shiyomi, M., Yasuda, T., Zhou, H.,
  et al. (2008). Small-scale species richness and its spatial variation
  in an alpine meadow on the Qinghai-Tibet Plateau. Ecological research,
  23, 657–663
</para>
          <para>
  Chizinski, C.J., Peterson, A., Hanowski, J., Blinn, C.R., Vondracek,
  B. &amp; Niemi, G. (2011). Breeding bird response to partially
  harvested riparian management zones. Forest Ecology and Management,
  261, 1892–1900
</para>
          <para>
  Clarke, F.M., Pio, D.V. &amp; Racey, P.A. (2005). A comparison of
  logging systems and bat diversity in the Neotropics. Conservation
  Biology, 19, 1194–1204
</para>
          <para>
  Clough, Y., Kruess, A. &amp; Tscharntke, T. (2007). Organic versus
  conventional arable farming systems: functional grouping helps
  understand staphylinid response. Agriculture, ecosystems &amp;
  environment, 118, 285–290
</para>
          <para>
  Cole, H.A., Newmaster, S.G., Lanteigne, L. &amp; Pitt, D. (2008).
  Long-term outcome of precommercial thinning on floristic diversity in
  north western New Brunswick, Canada. iForest-Biogeosciences and
  Forestry, 1, 145–156
</para>
          <para>
  Čop, J., Vidrih, M. &amp; Hacin, J. (2009). Influence of cutting
  regime and fertilizer application on the botanical composition, yield
  and nutritive value of herbage of wet grasslands in Central Europe.
  Grass and Forage Science, 64, 454–465
</para>
          <para>
  Crow, T.R., Buckley, D.S., Nauertz, E.A. &amp; Zasada, J.C. (2002).
  Effects of management on the composition and structure of northern
  hardwood forests in Upper Michigan. Forest Science, 48, 129–145
</para>
          <para>
  Decocq, G., Aubert, M., Dupont, F., Alard, D., Saguez, R.,
  Wattez-Franger, A., et al. (2004). Plant diversity in a managed
  temperate deciduous forest: understorey response to two silvicultural
  systems. Journal of Applied Ecology, 41, 1065–1079
</para>
          <para>
  Dickson, T.L. &amp; Gross, K.L. (2013). Plant community responses to
  long-term fertilization: changes in functional group abundance drive
  changes in species richness. Oecologia, 173, 1513–1520
</para>
          <para>
  Dolanc, C.R., Gorchov, D.L. &amp; Cornejo, F. (2003). The effects of
  silvicultural thinning on trees regenerating in strip clear-cuts in
  the Peruvian Amazon. Forest Ecology and Management, 182, 103–116
</para>
          <para>
  Drinkwater, L.E., Letourneau, D.K., Workneh, F., Van Bruggen, A.H.C.
  &amp; Shennan, C. (1995). Fundamental differences between conventional
  and organic tomato agroecosystems in California. Ecological
  applications, 5, 1098–1112
</para>
          <para>
  Edenius, L., Mikusiński, G., Witzell, J. &amp; Bergh, J. (2012).
  Effects of repeated fertilization of young Norway spruce on foliar
  phenolics and arthropods: implications for insectivorous birds’ food
  resources. Forest Ecology and Management, 277, 38–45
</para>
          <para>
  Edwards, D.P., Woodcock, P., Edwards, F.A., Larsen, T.H., Hsu, W.W.,
  Benedick, S., et al. (2012). Reduced-impact logging and biodiversity
  conservation: a case study from Borneo. Ecological Applications, 22,
  561–571
</para>
          <para>
  van Eekeren, N., de Boer, H., Bloem, J., Schouten, T., Rutgers, M., de
  Goede, R., et al. (2009). Soil biological quality of grassland
  fertilized with adjusted cattle manure slurries in comparison with
  organic and inorganic fertilizers. Biology and fertility of soils, 45,
  595–608
</para>
          <para>
  Etcheverry, P., Ouellet, J.-P. &amp; Crête, M. (2005). Response of
  small mammals to clear-cutting and precommercial thinning in mixed
  forests of southeastern Quebec. Canadian Journal of Forest Research,
  35, 2813–2822
</para>
          <para>
  Freemark, K.E. &amp; Kirk, D.A. (2001). Birds on organic and
  conventional farms in Ontario: partitioning effects of habitat and
  practices on species composition and abundance. Biological
  Conservation, 101, 337–350
</para>
          <para>
  Gabriel, D., Sait, S.M., Kunin, W.E. &amp; Benton, T.G. (2013). Food
  production vs. biodiversity: comparing organic and conventional
  agriculture. Journal of Applied Ecology, 50, 355–364
</para>
          <para>
  Gamoun, M. (2014). Grazing intensity effects on the vegetation in
  desert rangelands of Southern Tunisia. Journal of Arid Land, 6,
  324–333
</para>
          <para>
  Geiger, F., de Snoo, G.R., Berendse, F., Guerrero, I., Morales, M.B.,
  Onate, J.J., et al. (2010). Landscape composition influences farm
  management effects on farmland birds in winter: a pan-European
  approach. Agriculture, ecosystems &amp; environment, 139, 571–577
</para>
          <para>
  Ghazoul, J. (2002). Impact of logging on the richness and diversity of
  forest butterflies in a tropical dry forest in Thailand. Biodiversity
  &amp; Conservation, 11, 521–541
</para>
          <para>
  González-Alday, J., Martínez-Ruiz, C. &amp; Bravo, F. (2009).
  Evaluating different harvest intensities over understory plant
  diversity and pine seedlings, in a Pinus pinaster Ait. natural stand
  of Spain. Plant Ecology, 201, 211–220
</para>
          <para>
  Gourlet-Fleury, S., Mortier, F., Fayolle, A., Baya, F., Ouédraogo, D.,
  Bénédet, F., et al. (2013). Tropical forest recovery from logging: a
  24 year silvicultural experiment from Central Africa. Philosophical
  Transactions of the Royal Society of London B: Biological Sciences,
  368, 20120302
</para>
          <para>
  Greenberg, C.H., Harris, L.D. &amp; Neary, D.G. (1995). A comparison
  of bird communities in burned and salvage-logged, clearcut, and
  forested Florida sand pine scrub. The Wilson Bulletin, 107, 40–54
</para>
          <para>
  Greenberg, C.H. &amp; Thomas, M.C. (1995). Effects of forest
  management practices on terrestrial coleopteran assemblages in sand
  pine scrub. Florida entomologist, 78, 271–285
</para>
          <para>
  Grimbacher, P.S., Catterall, C.P., Kanowski, J. &amp; Proctor, H.C.
  (2007). Responses of ground-active beetle assemblages to different
  styles of reforestation on cleared rainforest land. Biodiversity and
  Conservation, 16, 2167–2184
</para>
          <para>
  Gross, N., Bloor, J.M., Louault, F., Maire, V. &amp; Soussana, J.-F.
  (2009). Effects of land-use change on productivity depend on
  small-scale plant species diversity. Basic and Applied Ecology, 10,
  687–696
</para>
          <para>
  Haeussler, S. &amp; Kabzems, R. (2005). Aspen plant community response
  to organic matter removal and soil compaction. Canadian journal of
  forest research, 35, 2030–2044
</para>
          <para>
  Hautier, Y., Seabloom, E.W., Borer, E.T., Adler, P.B., Harpole, W.S.,
  Hillebrand, H., et al. (2014). Eutrophication weakens stabilizing
  effects of diversity in natural grasslands. Nature, 508, 521–525
</para>
          <para>
  Haysom, K.A., McCracken, D.I., Foster, G.N. &amp; Sotherton, N.W.
  (2004). Developing grassland conservation headlands: response of
  carabid assemblage to different cutting regimes in a silage field
  edge. Agriculture, ecosystems &amp; environment, 102, 263–277
</para>
          <para>
  Hedwall, P.-O., Strengbom, J. &amp; Nordin, A. (2013). Can thinning
  alleviate negative effects of fertilization on boreal forest floor
  vegetation? Forest Ecology and Management, 310, 382–392
</para>
          <para>
  Hejcman, M., Češková, M., Schellberg, J. &amp; Pätzold, S. (2010). The
  Rengen Grassland Experiment: effect of soil chemical properties on
  biomass production, plant species composition and species richness.
  Folia Geobotanica, 45, 125–142
</para>
          <para>
  Higgins, S.I., Shackleton, C.M. &amp; Robinson, E.R. (1999). Changes
  in woody community structure and composition under constrasting
  landuse systems in a semi-arid savanna, South Africa. Journal of
  Biogeography, 26, 619–627
</para>
          <para>
  Holbech, L.H. (2005). The implications of selective logging and forest
  fragmentation for the conservation of avian diversity in evergreen
  forests of south-west Ghana. Bird Conservation International, 15,
  27–52
</para>
          <para>
  Hylander, K., Nilsson, C. &amp; Göthner, T. (2004). Effects of
  buffer-strip retention and clearcutting on land snails in boreal
  riparian forests. Conservation Biology, 18, 1052–1062
</para>
          <para>
  Imai, N., Seino, T., Aiba, S., Takyu, M., Titin, J. &amp; Kitayama, K.
  (2012). Effects of selective logging on tree species diversity and
  composition of Bornean tropical rain forests at different spatial
  scales. Plant Ecol, 213, 1413–1424
</para>
          <para>
  Isselstein, J., Griffith, B.A., Pradel, P. &amp; Venerus, S. (2007).
  Effects of livestock breed and grazing intensity on biodiversity and
  production in grazing systems. 1. Nutritive value of herbage and
  livestock performance. Grass and Forage Science, 62, 145–158
</para>
          <para>
  Jenkins, M.A. &amp; Parker, G.R. (1998). Composition and diversity of
  woody vegetation in silvicultural openings of southern Indiana
  forests. Forest Ecology and Management, 109, 57–74
</para>
          <para>
  Jones, D.T., Susilo, F.X., Bignell, D.E., Hardiwinoto, S., Gillison,
  A.N. &amp; Eggleton, P. (2003). Termite assemblage collapse along a
  land-use intensification gradient in lowland central Sumatra,
  Indonesia. Journal of Applied Ecology, 40, 380–391
</para>
          <para>
  Kaur, K., Jalota, R.K., Midmore, D.J. &amp; Rolfe, J. (2005). Pasture
  production in cleared and uncleared grazing systems of central
  Queensland, Australia. The Rangeland Journal, 27, 143–149
</para>
          <para>
  Kern, C.C., Palik, B.J. &amp; Strong, T.F. (2006). Ground-layer plant
  community responses to even-age and uneven-age silvicultural
  treatments in Wisconsin northern hardwood forests. Forest Ecology and
  Management, 230, 162–170
</para>
          <para>
  Klaus, V.H., Kleinebecker, T., Prati, D., Gossner, M.M., Alt, F.,
  Boch, S., et al. (2013). Does organic grassland farming benefit plant
  and arthropod diversity at the expense of yield and soil fertility?
  Agriculture, ecosystems &amp; environment, 177, 1–9
</para>
          <para>
  Klein, A.-M., Brittain, C., Hendrix, S.D., Thorp, R., Williams, N.
  &amp; Kremen, C. (2012). Wild pollination services to California
  almond rely on semi-natural habitat. Journal of Applied Ecology, 49,
  723–732
</para>
          <para>
  Kramberger, B. &amp; Kaligaric, M. (2008). Semi-natural grasslands:
  the effects of cutting frequency on long-term changes of floristic
  composition. Polish journal of Ecology, 56, 33
</para>
          <para>
  Krogmann, U., Rogers, B.F. &amp; Kumudini, S. (2008). Effects of
  mulching blueberry plants with cranberry fruits and leaves on yield,
  nutrient uptake and weed suppression. Compost Science &amp;
  Utilization, 16, 220–227
</para>
          <para>
  Laiolo, P., Caprio, E. &amp; Rolando, A. (2004). Can forest management
  have season-dependent effects on bird diversity? Biodiversity &amp;
  Conservation, 13, 1925–1941
</para>
          <para>
  Lanta, V., Doležal, J., Lantová, P., Kelíšek, J. &amp; Mudrák, O.
  (2009). Effects of pasture management and fertilizer regimes on
  botanical changes in species-rich mountain calcareous grassland in
  Central Europe. Grass and Forage Science, 64, 443–453
</para>
          <para>
  Lei, X., Lu, Y., Peng, C., Zhang, X., Chang, J. &amp; Hong, L. (2007).
  Growth and structure development of semi-natural larch-spruce-fir
  (Larix olgensis–Picea jezoensis–Abies nephrolepis) forests in
  northeast China: 12-year results after thinning. Forest Ecology and
  Management, 240, 165–177
</para>
          <para>
  Lomba, A., Vicente, J., Moreira, F. &amp; Honrado, J. (2011). Effects
  of multiple factors on plant diversity of forest fragments in
  intensive farmland of Northern Portugal. Forest Ecology and
  Management, 262, 2219–2228
</para>
          <para>
  Maeto, K. &amp; Sato, S. (2004). Impacts of forestry on ant species
  richness and composition in warm-temperate forests of Japan. Forest
  Ecology and Management, 187, 213–223
</para>
          <para>
  Mastrangelo, M.E. &amp; Gavin, M.C. (2012). Trade-offs between cattle
  production and bird conservation in an agricultural frontier of the
  Gran Chaco of Argentina. Conservation Biology, 26, 1040–1051
</para>
          <para>
  Mayer, R., Kaufmann, R., Vorhauser, K. &amp; Erschbamer, B. (2009).
  Effects of grazing exclusion on species composition in high-altitude
  grasslands of the Central Alps. Basic and Applied Ecology, 10, 447–455
</para>
          <para>
  Mosquera-Losada, M.R., Rodríguez-Barreira, S., López-Díaz, M.L.,
  Fernández-Núñez, E. &amp; Rigueiro-Rodríguez, A. (2009). Biodiversity
  and silvopastoral system use change in very acid soils. Agriculture,
  ecosystems &amp; environment, 131, 315–324
</para>
          <para>
  Mudrák, O., Doležal, J., Hájek, M., Dančák, M., Klimeš, L. &amp;
  Klimešová, J. (2013). Plant seedlings in a species-rich meadow: effect
  of management, vegetation type and functional traits. Applied
  Vegetation Science, 16, 286–295
</para>
          <para>
  Müller, J., Bußler, H. &amp; Kneib, T. (2008). Saproxylic beetle
  assemblages related to silvicultural management intensity and stand
  structures in a beech forest in Southern Germany. Journal of Insect
  Conservation, 12, 107–124
</para>
          <para>
  Müller, J., Engel, H. &amp; Blaschke, M. (2007). Assemblages of
  wood-inhabiting fungi related to silvicultural management intensity in
  beech forests in southern Germany. European Journal of Forest
  Research, 126, 513–527
</para>
          <para>
  Müller, J., Klaus, V.H., Kleinebecker, T., Prati, D., Hölzel, N. &amp;
  Fischer, M. (2012). Impact of land-use intensity and productivity on
  bryophyte diversity in agricultural grasslands. PloS one, 7, e51520
</para>
          <para>
  Murrieta-Galindo, R., González-Romero, A., López-Barrera, F. &amp;
  Parra-Olea, G. (2013). Coffee agrosystems: an important refuge for
  amphibians in central Veracruz, Mexico. Agroforestry systems, 87,
  767–779
</para>
          <para>
  Nagaike, T., Kamitani, T. &amp; Nakashizuka, T. (2005). Effects of
  different forest management systems on plant species diversity in a
  Fagus crenata forested landscape of central Japan. Canadian Journal of
  Forest Research, 35, 2832–2840
</para>
          <para>
  Norvez, O., Hébert, C. &amp; Bélanger, L. (2013). Impact of salvage
  logging on stand structure and beetle diversity in boreal balsam fir
  forest, 20 years after a spruce budworm outbreak. Forest Ecology and
  Management, 302, 122–132
</para>
          <para>
  Økland, T., Rydgren, K., Økland, R.H., Storaunet, K.O. &amp; Rolstad,
  J. (2003). Variation in environmental conditions, understorey species
  number, abundance and composition among natural and managed Picea
  abies forest stands. Forest Ecology and Management, 177, 17–37
</para>
          <para>
  Oomes, M.J.M. &amp; Van der Werf, A. (1996). Restoration of species
  diversity in grasslands: the effect of grassland management and
  changes in ground water level. Acta botanica gallica, 143, 451–461
</para>
          <para>
  Otto, R., García-del-Rey, E., Méndez, J. &amp; Fernández-Palacios,
  J.M. (2012). Effects of thinning on seed rain, regeneration and
  understory vegetation in a Pinus canariensis plantation (Tenerife,
  Canary Islands). Forest Ecology and Management, 280, 71–81
</para>
          <para>
  Paradis, S. &amp; Work, T.T. (2011). Partial cutting does not maintain
  spider assemblages within the observed range of natural variability in
  eastern Canadian black spruce forests. Forest Ecology and Management,
  262, 2079–2093
</para>
          <para>
  Parrotta, J.A., Francis, J.K. &amp; Knowles, O.H. (2002). Harvesting
  intensity affects forest structure and composition in an upland
  Amazonian forest. Forest ecology and management, 169, 243–255
</para>
          <para>
  Parthasarathy, N. (1999). Tree diversity and distribution in
  undisturbed and human-impacted sites of tropical wet evergreen forest
  in southern Western Ghats, India. Biodiversity &amp; Conservation, 8,
  1365–1381
</para>
          <para>
  Peeters, L.Y., Soto-Pinto, L., Perales, H., Montoya, G. &amp; Ishiki,
  M. (2003). Coffee production, timber, and firewood in traditional and
  Inga-shaded plantations in Southern Mexico. Agriculture, Ecosystems
  &amp; Environment, 95, 481–493
</para>
          <para>
  Penttilä, R., Siitonen, J. &amp; Kuusinen, M. (2004). Polypore
  diversity in managed and old-growth boreal Picea abies forests in
  southern Finland. Biological conservation, 117, 271–283
</para>
          <para>
  Pérez-Ramos, I.M., Zavala, M.A., Marañón, T., Díaz-Villa, M.D. &amp;
  Valladares, F. (2008). Dynamics of understorey herbaceous plant
  diversity following shrub clearing of cork oak forests: a five-year
  study. Forest Ecology and Management, 255, 3242–3253
</para>
          <para>
  Philpott, S.M., Bichier, P., Rice, R.A. &amp; Greenberg, R. (2008).
  Biodiversity conservation, yield, and alternative products in coffee
  agroecosystems in Sumatra, Indonesia. Biodiversity and Conservation,
  17, 1805–1820
</para>
          <para>
  Rotenberg, J.A. &amp; Stouffer, P.C. (2007). Ecological role of a tree
  (Gmelina arborea) plantation in Guatemala: an assessment of an
  alternative land use for tropical avian conservation. The Auk, 124,
  316–330
</para>
          <para>
  Ruan, W.-B., Ren, T., Chen, Q., Zhu, X. &amp; Wang, J.-G. (2013).
  Effects of conventional and reduced N inputs on nematode communities
  and plant yield under intensive vegetable production. Applied soil
  ecology, 66, 48–55
</para>
          <para>
  Sasaki, T., Yoshihara, Y., Suyama, Y. &amp; Nakashizuka, T. (2011).
  Clipping stimulates productivity but not diversity in improved and
  semi-natural pastures in temperate Japan. Agriculture, ecosystems
  &amp; environment, 142, 428–431
</para>
          <para>
  Schmitt, C.B., Senbeta, F., Denich, M., Preisinger, H. &amp; Boehmer,
  H.J. (2010). Wild coffee management and plant diversity in the montane
  rainforest of southwestern Ethiopia. African Journal of Ecology, 48,
  78–86
</para>
          <para>
  Schon, N.L., Mackay, A.D., Gray, R.A.J. &amp; Minor, M.A. (2011).
  Influence of phosphorus inputs and sheep treading on soil macrofauna
  and mesofauna in hill pastures. New Zealand Journal of Agricultural
  Research, 54, 83–96
</para>
          <para>
  Scursoni, J.A. &amp; Satorre, E.H. (2010). Glyphosate management
  strategies, weed diversity and soybean yield in Argentina. Crop
  Protection, 29, 957–962
</para>
          <para>
  Sebastià, M.-T., Palero, N. &amp; de Bello, F. (2011). Changes in
  management modify agro-diversity in sainfoin swards in the Eastern
  Pyrenees. Agronomy for sustainable development, 31, 533–540
</para>
          <para>
  Seiwa, K., Eto, Y., Hishita, M. &amp; Masaka, K. (2012). Effects of
  thinning intensity on species diversity and timber production in a
  conifer (Cryptomeria japonica) plantation in Japan. Journal of forest
  research, 17, 468–478
</para>
          <para>
  Sekercioglu, C.H. (2002). Effects of forestry practices on vegetation
  structure and bird community of Kibale National Park, Uganda.
  Biological Conservation, 107, 229–240
</para>
          <para>
  Sippola, A.-L., Siitonen, J. &amp; Punttila, P. (2002). Beetle
  diversity in timberline forests: a comparison between old-growth and
  regeneration areas in Finnish Lapland. In: Annales Zoologici Fennici.
  pp. 69–86
</para>
          <para>
  Sircely, J. &amp; Naeem, S. (2013). Relationships of overstory trees
  and shrubs with forage species portray ecosystem service interactions
  in smallholder fallows. Agroforestry systems, 87, 451–464
</para>
          <para>
  Sirrine, J.R., Letourneau, D.K., Shennan, C., Sirrine, D., Fouch, R.,
  Jackson, L., et al. (2008). Impacts of groundcover management systems
  on yield, leaf nutrients, weeds, and arthropods of tart cherry in
  Michigan, USA. Agriculture, ecosystems &amp; environment, 125, 239–245
</para>
          <para>
  Slade, E.M., Mann, D.J. &amp; Lewis, O.T. (2011). Biodiversity and
  ecosystem function of tropical forest dung beetles under contrasting
  logging regimes. Biological Conservation, 144, 166–174
</para>
          <para>
  Smith, R.S. &amp; Rushton, S.P. (1994). The effects of grazing
  management on the vegetation of mesotrophic (meadow) grassland in
  Northern England. Journal of Applied Ecology, 13–24
</para>
          <para>
  Smith, R.S., Shiel, R.S., Millward, D. &amp; Corkhill, P. (2000). The
  interactive effects of management on the productivity and plant
  community structure of an upland meadow: an 8-year field trial.
  Journal of Applied Ecology, 37, 1029–1043
</para>
          <para>
  Solomou, A. &amp; Sfougaris, A. (2011). Comparing conventional and
  organic olive groves in central Greece: plant and bird diversity and
  abundance. Renewable Agriculture and Food Systems, 26, 297–316
</para>
          <para>
  Sullivan, T.P., Sullivan, D.S. &amp; Lindgren, P.M. (2008). Influence
  of variable retention harvests on forest ecosystems: Plant and mammal
  responses up to 8 years post-harvest. Forest Ecology and Management,
  254, 239–254
</para>
          <para>
  Sullivan, T.P., Sullivan, D.S., Lindgren, P.M. &amp; Boateng, J.O.
  (2002). Influence of conventional and chemical thinning on stand
  structure and diversity of plant and mammal communities in young
  lodgepole pine forest. Forest Ecology and Management, 170, 173–187
</para>
          <para>
  Sullivan, T.P., Sullivan, D.S. &amp; Lindgren, P.M.F. (2001). Stand
  Structure and Small Mammals in Young Lodgepole Pine Forest: 10-Year
  Results After Thinning. Ecological Applications, 11, 1151–1173
</para>
          <para>
  Summerville, K.S. (2011). Managing the forest for more than the trees:
  effects of experimental timber harvest on forest Lepidoptera.
  Ecological Applications, 21, 806–816
</para>
          <para>
  Summerville, K.S. &amp; Crist, T.O. (2002). Effects of timber harvest
  on forest Lepidoptera: community, guild, and species responses.
  Ecological Applications, 12, 820–835
</para>
          <para>
  Thompson, I.D., Kirk, D.A. &amp; Jastrebski, C. (2013). Does
  postharvest silviculture improve convergence of avian communities in
  managed and old-growth boreal forests? Canadian Journal of Forest
  Research, 43, 1050–1062
</para>
          <para>
  Toivanen, T. &amp; Kotiaho, J.S. (2007). Mimicking natural
  disturbances of boreal forests: the effects of controlled burning and
  creating dead wood on beetle diversity. Biodiversity and Conservation,
  16, 3193–3211
</para>
          <para>
  Tozer, D.C., Burke, D.M., Nol, E. &amp; Elliott, K.A. (2010).
  Short-term effects of group-selection harvesting on breeding birds in
  a northern hardwood forest. Forest Ecology and Management, 259,
  1522–1529
</para>
          <para>
  Van Gemerden, B.S., Shu, G.N. &amp; Olff, H. (2003). Recovery of
  conservation values in Central African rain forest after logging and
  shifting cultivation. Biodiversity &amp; Conservation, 12, 1553–1570
</para>
          <para>
  Vasseur, L., Cloutier, C. &amp; Ansseau, C. (2000). Effects of
  repeated sewage sludge application on plant community diversity and
  structure under agricultural field conditions on Podzolic soils in
  eastern Quebec. Agriculture, ecosystems &amp; environment, 81, 209–216
</para>
          <para>
  Vidal, S. &amp; others. (2008). Plant biodiversity and vegetation
  structure in traditional cocoa forest gardens in southern Cameroon
  under different management. Biodiversity and Conservation, 17,
  1821–1835
</para>
          <para>
  Vintu, V., Samuil, C., Sirbu, C., Popovici, C.I. &amp; Stavarache, M.
  (2011). Sustainable management of Nardus stricta L. grasslands in
  Romania’s Carpathians. Notulae Botanicae Horti Agrobotanici
  Cluj-Napoca, 39, 142
</para>
          <para>
  Wampler, C.R., Frey, J.K., VanLeeuwen, D.M., Boren, J.C. &amp; Baker,
  T.T. (2008). Mammals in mechanically thinned and non-thinned
  mixed-coniferous forest in the Sacramento Mountains, New Mexico. The
  Southwestern Naturalist, 53, 431–443
</para>
          <para>
  Wan, K., Tao, Y., Li, R., Pan, J., Tang, L. &amp; Chen, F. (2012).
  Influences of long-term different types of fertilization on weed
  community biodiversity in rice paddy fields. Weed biology and
  management, 12, 12–21
</para>
          <para>
  Wang, K.-H., McSorley, R., Bohlen, P. &amp; Gathumbi, S.M. (2006).
  Cattle grazing increases microbial biomass and alters soil nematode
  communities in subtropical pastures. Soil Biology and Biochemistry,
  38, 1956–1965
</para>
          <para>
  Wardle, D.A., Nicholson, K.S., Bonner, K.I. &amp; Yeates, G.W. (1999).
  Effects of agricultural intensification on soil-associated arthropod
  population dynamics, community structure, diversity and temporal
  variability over a seven-year period. Soil Biology and Biochemistry,
  31, 1691–1706
</para>
          <para>
  Yan, X.L., Bao, W.K., Pang, X.Y., Zhang, N.X. &amp; Chen, J. (2013).
  Regeneration strategies influence ground bryophyte composition and
  diversity after forest clearcutting. Annals of forest science, 70,
  845–861
</para></section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <project>
      <title>National Socio-Environmental Synthesis Center</title>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Margaret</givenName>
          <surName>Palmer</surName>
        </individualName>
        <role>Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <funding>Division of Biological Infrastructure, National Science Foundation (NSF) 1052875</funding>
      <relatedProject>
        <title>German Centre for Integrative Biodiversity Research (iDiv) Halle-Jena-Leipzig</title>
        <personnel>
          <individualName>
            <givenName>Christian</givenName>
            <surName>Wirth</surName>
          </individualName>
          <role>Principal Investigator</role>
        </personnel>
        <funding>The Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG) DFG FZT 118</funding>
      </relatedProject>
      <relatedProject>
        <title>Global modelling of local biodiversity responses to human impacts</title>
        <personnel>
          <individualName>
            <givenName>A.</givenName>
            <givenName>J.</givenName>
            <surName>Purvis</surName>
          </individualName>
          <role>Principal Investigator</role>
        </personnel>
        <funding>UK Natural Environment Research Council NE/L012995/1</funding>
      </relatedProject>
      <relatedProject>
        <title>Collaborative research: Demographic heterogeneity at landscape scales in an emergent invasive species, Centaurea stoebe, in New York State</title>
        <personnel>
          <individualName>
            <givenName>Jessica</givenName>
            <surName>Gurevitch</surName>
          </individualName>
          <role>Principal Investigator</role>
        </personnel>
        <funding>Division of Environmental Biology, National Science Foundation (NSF) 1119891</funding>
      </relatedProject>
      <relatedProject>
        <title>Operational Potential of Ecosystem Research Applications (OPERA)</title>
        <personnel>
          <individualName>
            <givenName>(unkown, administered by the University of Edinburgh, United Kingdom)</givenName>
            <surName>(unkown)</surName>
          </individualName>
          <role>Principal Investigator</role>
        </personnel>
        <funding>The European Union 7th Framework Program (FP7-ENVIRONMENT) 308393</funding>
      </relatedProject>
      <relatedProject>
        <title>GLUES - Global Assessment of Land Use Dynamics, Greenhouse Gas Emissions and Ecosystem Services</title>
        <personnel>
          <individualName>
            <givenName>Cornelia</givenName>
            <surName>Paulsch</surName>
          </individualName>
          <role>Principal Investigator</role>
        </personnel>
        <funding>German Federal Ministry of Education and Research 01LL0901A</funding>
      </relatedProject>
    </project>
    <dataTable>
      <entityName>gcb14606-sup-0002-supinfo_1.csv</entityName>
      <entityDescription>data on species richness</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>gcb14606-sup-0002-supinfo_1.csv</objectName>
        <size unit="bytes">45473</size>
        <authentication method="MD5">f47cc33d3ebc13698328e5ff28e6f98b</authentication>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
              <quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
      </physical>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Study_Case</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Name of study from which the data is taken</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Name of study from which the data is taken</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Longitude</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Longitude of study site</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>degree</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">-122.4175</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">175.25</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Latitude</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Latitude of study site</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>degree</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">-37.8</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">68.416667</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>LUI_range_level</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Landuse intensity (classified according to table 1)</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Landuse intensity (classified according to table 1)</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Species_Group</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Broad class of species group, i.e. vertebrates, invertebrates, and plants.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Broad class of species group, i.e. vertebrates, invertebrates, and plants.</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Product</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Broad class of harvested product, i.e. crop, green fodder, and wood.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Broad class of harvested product, i.e. crop, green fodder, and wood.</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>main_climate</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Broad climate zone according to the Köppen-Geiger climate classification, i.e. polar, cold (continental), temperate, arid, and tropical.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Broad climate zone according to the Köppen-Geiger climate classification, i.e. polar, cold (continental), temperate, arid, and tropical.</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>landuse_history</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Broad class of time of first significant use (table 3), i.e. 5950 BC, 50 BC, 1450, 1950, after 1950. And categorized according to the major developments of agriculture.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Broad class of time of first significant use (table 3), i.e. 5950 BC, 50 BC, 1450, 1950, after 1950. And categorized according to the major developments of agriculture.</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>ES_and_BD</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>An indication of whether species richness and yield are measured from the same species group, in which case species richness and production are considered to be “linked” rather than “independent”.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>An indication of whether species richness and yield are measured from the same species group, in which case species richness and production are considered to be “linked” rather than “independent”.</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Richness_Plot_Size</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Plot size</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>squareMeter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">0.01</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">250000</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>not available</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Log_RR</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Log transformed response ratio of species richness with changing land use intensity</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">-2.321453577</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">1.981920587</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>not available</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Log_RR_Var</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Variance of log transformed response ratio</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">0.000179999</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">0.705503536</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>not available</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Mean_Low</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Mean richness of the lower intensity land use</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">0.3</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">192</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>not available</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>SD_Low</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Standard deviation of richness of lower intensity land use</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">41.41</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>not available</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>N_Low</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Sample size of lower intensity land use</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>natural</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">2</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">414</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>not available</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Mean_High</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Mean richness of the higher intensity land use</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">0.2</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">168</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>not available</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>SD_High</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Standard deviation of richness of higher intensity land use</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">29.05</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>not available</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>N_High</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Sample size of higher intensity land use</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>natural</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">2</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">576</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>not available</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>SD_is_imputed_Low</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Whether the standard deviation of species richness in lower intensity land-use was imputed (done in case this information was missing in the original study, done using means matching)</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Whether the standard deviation of species richness in lower intensity land-use was imputed (done in case this information was missing in the original study, done using means matching)</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>SD_is_imputed_High</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Whether the standard deviation of species richness in higher intensity land-use was imputed (done in case this information was missing in the original study, done using means matching)</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Whether the standard deviation of species richness in higher intensity land-use was imputed (done in case this information was missing in the original study, done using means matching)</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
      <numberOfRecords>292</numberOfRecords>
    </dataTable>
    <dataTable>
      <entityName>gcb14606-sup-0002-supinfo_2.csv</entityName>
      <entityDescription>data on yield</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>gcb14606-sup-0002-supinfo_2.csv</objectName>
        <size unit="bytes">24000</size>
        <authentication method="MD5">faa83804cf73ca26752b32cc4e07ab25</authentication>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
              <quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
      </physical>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Study_Case</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Name of study from which the data is taken</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Name of study from which the data is taken</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Longitude</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Longitude of study site</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>degree</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">-122.4175</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">175.25</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Latitude</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Latitude of study site</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>degree</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">-37.8</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">68.416667</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>LUI_range_level</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Landuse intensity (classified according to table 1)</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Landuse intensity (classified according to table 1)</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Product</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Broad class of harvested product, i.e. crop, green fodder, and wood.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Broad class of harvested product, i.e. crop, green fodder, and wood.</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>main_climate</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Broad climate zone according to the Köppen-Geiger climate classification, i.e. polar, cold (continental), temperate, arid, and tropical.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Broad climate zone according to the Köppen-Geiger climate classification, i.e. polar, cold (continental), temperate, arid, and tropical.</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>landuse_history</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Broad class of time of first significant use (table 3), i.e. 5950 BC, 50 BC, 1450, 1950, after 1950. And categorized according to the major developments of agriculture.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Broad class of time of first significant use (table 3), i.e. 5950 BC, 50 BC, 1450, 1950, after 1950. And categorized according to the major developments of agriculture.</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>LU_definition_and_ES</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>An indication of whether land-use intensity step is based on yield, in which case yield is considered to be “linked” to intensity rather than “independent”. For example the harvesting technique in forest (e.g. clear cut, selective logging) is used to define the land-use intensity class and also determines the amount of extracted yield.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>An indication of whether land-use intensity step is based on yield, in which case yield is considered to be “linked” to intensity rather than “independent”. For example the harvesting technique in forest (e.g. clear cut, selective logging) is used to define the land-use intensity class and also determines the amount of extracted yield.</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Yield_Unit_Type</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Type of unit used to measure yield</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Type of unit used to measure yield</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Log_RR</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Log transformed response ratio of yield with changing land use intensity</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">-1.853296634</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">2.740840024</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>not available</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Log_RR_Var</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Variance of log transformed response ratio</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">4.36462e-05</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">3.054180688</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>not available</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Mean_Low</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Mean yield from the lower intensity land use</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">0.07</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">15248.6667</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>not available</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>SD_Low</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Standard deviation of yield from lower intensity land use</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">0.02</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">3887.75</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>not available</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>N_Low</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Sample size of lower intensity land use</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">2</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">1149</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>not available</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Mean_High</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Mean yield from higher intensity land use</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">0.28</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">13738</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>not available</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>SD_High</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Standard deviation of yield from higher intensity land use</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">0.08</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">3580.95</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>not available</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>N_High</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Sample size of higher intensity land use</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">2</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">1149</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>not available</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>SD_is_imputed_Low</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Whether the standard deviation of yield from lower intensity land-use was imputed (done in case this information was missing in the original study, done using means matching)</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Whether the standard deviation of yield from lower intensity land-use was imputed (done in case this information was missing in the original study, done using means matching)</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>SD_is_imputed_High</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Whether the standard deviation of yield from higher intensity land-use was imputed (done in case this information was missing in the original study, done using means matching)</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Whether the standard deviation of yield from higher intensity land-use was imputed (done in case this information was missing in the original study, done using means matching)</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
      <numberOfRecords>157</numberOfRecords>
    </dataTable>
    <otherEntity>
      <entityName>protocol.pdf</entityName>
      <entityDescription>Formatted methods</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>protocol.pdf</objectName>
        <size unit="bytes">304744</size>
        <authentication method="MD5">f2e7f5fa3505a219793dafcd0c1645f5</authentication>
        <dataFormat>
          <externallyDefinedFormat>
            <formatName>unknown</formatName>
          </externallyDefinedFormat>
        </dataFormat>
      </physical>
      <entityType>unknown</entityType>
    </otherEntity>
  </dataset>
</eml:eml>
